<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[A Long Story]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib\media\favicon.png</url><title>A Long Story</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:33:11 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib\rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:33:10 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Highstorms]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="DALL·E 2024-03-10 19.22.11 - A visual representation of Highstorms, a powerful and ominous force from a fantasy world. The scene depicts dark, tumultuous clouds swirling in a chao.webp" src="\lib\media\dall·e-2024-03-10-19.22.11-a-visual-representation-of-highstorms,-a-powerful-and-ominous-force-from-a-fantasy-world.-the-scene-depicts-dark,-tumultuous-clouds-swirling-in-a-chao.webp"><br><br>Highstorms are a catastrophic natural phenomenon, characterized by their devastating impact on both the physical and metaphysical realms. Unlike conventional storms, Highstorms manifest with disconcerting moments of darkness instead of lightning flashes and emit high-pitched, eerie sounds rather than deep, rolling thunder. <br><br>Highstorms originated from the extensive and unrestrained use of weather manipulation magic by mages in a period predating the <a data-href="Era of Legends" href="\timelines\era-of-legends.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Legends</a> and the adoption of the Druidic Calendar. This form of magic, wielded to shape the world's climate, led to awe-inspiring changes but also had dangerous, unforeseen consequences. The Highstorms were an unintended side effect of this manipulation, disrupting the natural order and posing a severe threat to all known life.<br><br>
<br>Dark Flashes: Instead of traditional lightning, Highstorms produce moments of darkness that tear through the atmosphere.
<br>Eerie Sounds: The storms are accompanied by high-pitched, unsettling screeches, replacing the typical sound of thunder.
<br>Destructive Force: Highstorms possess the power to disrupt both the physical world and the fabric of reality itself, making them a dire threat to the known world.
<br><br>The emergence of Highstorms led to a schism among magic users. While many mages continued their pursuits, oblivious or indifferent to the consequences, a faction known as the Druids recognized the gravity of the situation. This division culminated in brutal magical wars, with casualties too numerous to count. Ultimately, the Druids emerged victorious, determined to rectify the mistakes of the past and banish the Highstorms.<br><br><a data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Druidic Sacrifice</a> marks the most pivotal and solemn event in the annals of the known world, signaling the end of the Era of Storms. Faced with the catastrophic impact of the Highstorms, the Druid Circles united in a secretive, large-scale ritual aimed at banishing the storms beyond the borders of the known world. This effort, however, came at an extraordinary cost: every Druid involved sacrificed their life, marking the ritual with a profound loss.<br>
The Druidic Sacrifice is commemorated as the official beginning of the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Time and the Calendar" data-href="Time and the Calendar" href="\timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a> and is a crucial part of Druidic heritage. It serves as a solemn reminder of the dangers of unchecked magical manipulation and the importance of preserving the natural order. Today, the manipulation of weather is outlawed across the world, sometimes even under penalty of death, as societies seek to prevent the recurrence of such cataclysms.<br><br>The nature of Highstorms and how they came about, led some people to believe there to be a higher power responsible for them, one who did not like how much magic users meddled with their affairs. They founded the <a data-href="Order of the Storms" href="\Order of the Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Order of the Storms</a>, a dark cult that tries to get rid of all magic users.<br><br>What lies beyond the Highstorms remains one of the greatest mysteries of the known world. The storms serve as a barrier, encapsulating the known world and keeping its inhabitants from discovering what lies beyond. Despite this, the Druids and other custodians of the world's natural order continue their vigil, ensuring that the Highstorms remain at bay and that the balance of the world is maintained.]]></description><link>fantastical-elements\highstorms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Fantastical Elements/Highstorms.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:31:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\dall·e-2024-03-10-19.22.11-a-visual-representation-of-highstorms,-a-powerful-and-ominous-force-from-a-fantasy-world.-the-scene-depicts-dark,-tumultuous-clouds-swirling-in-a-chao.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\dall·e-2024-03-10-19.22.11-a-visual-representation-of-highstorms,-a-powerful-and-ominous-force-from-a-fantasy-world.-the-scene-depicts-dark,-tumultuous-clouds-swirling-in-a-chao.webp"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Orcs]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
"In the shadow of storms and legends, the Orcs of Caitha stand tall, their spirits tempered by the trials of the past and their hearts guided by the virtues of honor and resilience."

<br>from "A Traveler's Guide to Brurogh", by Casper Mossbane

<br><br><br>Orcs are imposing figures, with muscular builds that speak to their warrior heritage. They typically stand over six feet tall, with green to gray skin that can sometimes carry a bluish hue. Their tusks, emerging from the lower jaw, are a mark of their race, varying in size but always present as a symbol of their strength and ferocity. Their eyes, often gold or red, shine with a depth of wisdom and the fire of their indomitable spirit. They have rough, leathery skin, thick bones and rock hard muscles, making them suited for physically demanding tasks.<br><br>Orcs living in areas with many other races are often perceived as somewhat rude or "standoffish," if not hostile, because they neither ask for help nor offer help, even in times of crisis, and are offended if someone tries to help unsolicited. There are rumors that they steal children, because if an Orc finds a child lost in the forest, they will feed it and - if they cannot find the parents or home - raise and integrate it.<br><br>Central to Orcish society is their spirituality, revolving around the worship of <a data-href="Garrosh" href="\religions\deities\garrosh.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Garrosh</a>, a deity of justice and honor. This spirituality guides their daily lives, emphasizing personal growth through adversity and the importance of community responsibility, especially towards children.<br>
Orcish spirituality states that a soul can only grow and become stronger by overcoming the challenges life presents to them. The challenge of supporting or interfering with someone else unsolicited is not only impolite but very hurtful - because you are taking away their chance to grow. Asking for help is something very personal, and doing so could be a way for an Orc to bond or be "too personal/intimate," depending on the existing relationship with the person. Children are an exception - for Orcs, all children are fundamentally the responsibility of the society/community, no matter whose child it is or whether the child is an Orc at all.<br><br>Orcish cuisine is hearty, reflecting their hunting and gathering heritage. Dishes often feature game, roots, and wild vegetables, seasoned with the herbs of the Katarisian forests. A common meal might include roasted boar, forest mushrooms, and a brew made from fermented berries.<br><br>Orcish names sound powerful and imposing, and are usually bestowed upon them in a ceremony by their parents or caretakers. They don't usually carry last names.<br><br>Garthok, Ertok, Nartha, Gnarg, Yargol, Nakgu, Durbul, Garothmuk<br><br>Hit points: 10<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Strength, Free<br>
Ability Flaws:  -<br><br>Common, <a data-href="Orcish" href="\Orcish" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Orcish</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=19" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=19</a><br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br><br>The early history of the Orcs is marked by their struggle for survival in a stone-age world. They lived in close-knit nomadic tribes, relying on their strength and cunning to hunt and the wisdom of their elders to navigate the challenges of their environment. <br><br>This period brought catastrophic magical storms that ravaged Caitha, reshaping the land and testing the Orcs like never before. Their resilience during these times was unmatched, as they adapted to the chaos, protecting their communities and growing strong resentments towards the magic that flowed through their world in turmoil. Many tribes started to settle for more permanent homes for better protection.<br><br>After the storms were banished, the Orcs entered a period of rebuilding and growth. It was a time of heroes and legends, where the greatest tales of Orcish valor and wisdom were forged. Societies became more structured and the Orcs' deep respect for the natural world led them to form alliances with other races, sharing their knowledge of survival and spirituality.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\orcs.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Orcs.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:09:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Common Ancestries]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>All the inhabitants of Caitha, as far as we know, are part of one of the following sapient species:<br>
If you find something on <a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/</a> that you don't find listed here but really want to play, talk to your GM, maybe you can figure something out together.<br><br>
<br>
<a data-href="Dwarves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\dwarves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dwarves</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Orcs" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\orcs.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Orcs</a>

<br>
This page is very much under construction and will be expanded soon. The following ancestries are currently planned to be added:

<br>
<a data-href="Elves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\elves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Elves</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Gnomes" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\gnomes.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Gnomes</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Goblins" href="\Goblins" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Goblins</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Humans" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\humans.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Humans</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Grippli" href="\Grippli" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Grippli</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Leshy" href="\Leshy" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Leshy</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Lizardfolk" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\lizardfolk.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Lizardfolk</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Vanaras" href="\Vanaras" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Vanaras</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Automatons" href="\Automatons" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Automatons</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Fleshwarps" href="\Fleshwarps" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fleshwarps</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Poppets" href="\Poppets" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Poppets</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a>

<br>
<a data-href="Mossin (Halflings)" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\mossin-(halflings).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mossin (Halflings)</a>

<br>
]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 15:10:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Caitha]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="logo.png" src="\_attachments\logo.png" style="width: 650px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><br>Welcome to Caitha, dear reader.<br>
This worldbuilding project has been and still is a great journey that began in 2018, but has its roots in my childhood fascination with worldbuilding.<br>
I can trace this fascination back to about the age of 7, where my early attempts at map-making gave birth to many Island Nations, each proudly bearing the name "Joshuania".<br>
These miniature realms, with their train stations, sun-kissed beaches and grocery stores were my 7-year-old-self's vision of the perfect country, led, of course, by none other than me.<br>Now, with Caitha, my ambition has evolved. My goal is to breathe life into the fantasy world that has been brewing in my notes over the years, a world teaming with magic, history, and untold adventures. Caitha isn't just a static creation; it's a canvas for stories I might tell, a potential stage for epic quests in games like DnD or Pathfinder, or a backdrop for stories in whatever types of mediums I want to explore.<br>But even if I never venture beyond chronicling the history or writing about flora and fauna of Caitha, that's perfectly fine. The real joy for me at the moment lies in the act of building, in creating, in getting lost in the tapestry of this world, which is, in my mind, a lot more than I am currently capable of writing down.<br>So, whether you're here to explore or because I sent you the link eager to get some feedback on if the site is finally working or not:<br>
Welcome to Caitha.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Table of Elements" data-href="Table of Elements" href="\table-of-elements.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Enter</a><br><br><a data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Druidic Sacrifice</a>, a tale of sacrifice and the beginning of timekeeping.]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:09:37 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="_attachments\logo.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="_attachments\logo.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Table of Elements]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="logo.png" src="\_attachments\logo.png" style="width: 650px; max-width: 100%;"><br>the following list is structured after the "worldbuilding Table of Elements" by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.reddit.com/r/worldbuilding/comments/u55hfb/worldbuilding_table_of_elements/" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/worldbuilding/comments/u55hfb/worldbuilding_table_of_elements/" target="_blank">u/otherAtlas</a><br>
traveler, beware! many articles listed here are not published yet and are still being refined<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Maps" href="\maps\maps.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Maps</a>
<br><a data-href="Timelines" href="\timelines\timelines.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Timelines</a> *
<br><a data-href="Time and the Calendar" href="\timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Time and the Calendar</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Ancestries" href="\player-character-options\ancestries.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ancestries</a> *
<br><a data-href="Heritages" href="\Heritages" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Heritages</a> *
<br><a data-href="Backgrounds" href="\Backgrounds" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Backgrounds</a>*
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Continents" href="\geographic-elements\continents.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Continents</a>
<br><a data-href="Seas and Oceans" href="\Seas and Oceans" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Seas and Oceans</a> *
<br><a data-href="Rivers and Lakes" href="\Rivers and Lakes" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Rivers and Lakes</a> *
<br><a data-href="States and Nations" href="\States and Nations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">States and Nations</a> *
<br><a data-href="Cities" href="\Cities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Towns" href="\Towns" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Towns</a> *
<br><a data-href="Villages &amp; Smaller" href="\Villages &amp; Smaller" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Villages &amp; Smaller</a> *
<br><br>Caitha has a temperate climate, with temperatures ranging from -50 degrees Celsius up to 40 degrees Celsius. The Surface of Caitha is mostly covered in oceans.<br>
<br><a data-href="Flora" href="\flora\flora.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Flora</a> *
<br><a data-href="Fauna" href="\fauna\fauna.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fauna</a> *
<br><a data-href="Ecosystems" href="\ecosystems\ecosystems.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ecosystems</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Architecture" href="\Architecture" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Architecture</a> *
<br><a data-href="Art" href="\Art" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Art</a> *
<br><a data-href="Fashion" href="\Fashion" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fashion</a> *
<br><a data-href="Cuisine" href="\Cuisine" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cuisine</a> *
<br><a data-href="Etiquette and Taboos" href="\Etiquette and Taboos" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Etiquette and Taboos</a> *
<br><a data-href="Entertainment" href="\Entertainment" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Entertainment</a> *
<br><a data-href="Body Adornment" href="\Body Adornment" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Body Adornment</a>s *
<br><a data-href="Rituals" href="\Rituals" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Rituals</a> *
<br><a data-href="Celebrations" href="\Celebrations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Celebrations</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Guilds and other Organizations" href="\guilds\guilds-and-other-organizations.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Guilds and other Organizations</a>
<br><a data-href="Hierarchies" href="\Hierarchies" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hierarchies</a> *
<br><a data-href="Heraldry and Vexillology" href="\Heraldry and Vexillology" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Heraldry and Vexillology</a> *
<br><a data-href="Calendars" href="\Calendars" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Calendars</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Recorded Histories" href="\Recorded Histories" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Recorded Histories</a> *
<br><a data-href="Legends and Tales" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Legends and Tales</a>
<br><a data-href="Artifacts" href="\Artifacts" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Artifacts</a> *
<br><a data-href="Ruins" href="\Ruins" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ruins</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Alphabets and Languages" href="\Alphabets and Languages" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Alphabets and Languages</a> *
<br><a data-href="Figures of Speech" href="\Figures of Speech" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Figures of Speech</a> *
<br><a data-href="Slangs and Curses" href="\Slangs and Curses" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Slangs and Curses</a> *
<br><a data-href="Lies and Propaganda" href="\Lies and Propaganda" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Lies and Propaganda</a> *
<br><a data-href="Long Distance Communication" href="\Long Distance Communication" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Long Distance Communication</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Tools" href="\Tools" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Tools</a> *
<br><a data-href="Arms and Armour" href="\Arms and Armour" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Arms and Armour</a> *
<br><a data-href="Medicine" href="\Medicine" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Medicine</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Governments" href="\Governments" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Governments</a> *
<br><a data-href="Diplomacy and Politics" href="\Diplomacy and Politics" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Diplomacy and Politics</a> *
<br><a data-href="Political Events" href="\Political Events" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Political Events</a> *
<br><a data-href="War" href="\War" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">War</a> *
<br><a data-href="Law and Order" href="\Law and Order" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Law and Order</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Currencies and Trade" href="\economics\currencies-and-trade.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Currencies and Trade</a> *
<br><a data-href="Businesses and Corporations" href="\Businesses and Corporations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Businesses and Corporations</a> *
<br><a data-href="Rare Goods" href="\Rare Goods" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Rare Goods</a> *
<br><a data-href="Resources" href="\Resources" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Resources</a> *
<br><a data-href="Important Trade Routes" href="\Important Trade Routes" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Important Trade Routes</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Deities" href="\Deities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Deities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Religions" href="\Religions" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Religions</a> *
<br><a data-href="Sacred Texts" href="\Sacred Texts" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Sacred Texts</a> *
<br><a data-href="Afterlife Beliefs" href="\Afterlife Beliefs" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Afterlife Beliefs</a> *
<br><a data-href="Prophecies" href="\Prophecies" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Prophecies</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Magic/Magic in Caitha" href="\magic\magic-in-caitha.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magic/Magic in Caitha</a> *

<br><a data-href="Magic Language" href="\languages\magic-language.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magic Language</a> *
<br><a data-href="Druidic Magic" href="\Druidic Magic" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Magic</a> *
<br><a data-href="Magical Creatures" href="\Magical Creatures" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magical Creatures</a> *
<br><a data-href="Unique Abilities" href="\Unique Abilities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Unique Abilities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Constructed Itelligences" href="\Constructed Itelligences" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Constructed Itelligences</a> *
<br><a data-href="Magic Rituals" href="\Magic Rituals" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magic Rituals</a> *


<br><a data-href="Paranormal Entities" href="\Paranormal Entities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Paranormal Entities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Stars" href="\Stars" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Stars</a> *
<br><a data-href="Planets" href="\Planets" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Planets</a> *
<br><a data-href="Moons" href="\Moons" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moons</a> *
<br><a data-href="Asteroids" href="\Asteroids" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Asteroids</a> *
<br><a data-href="Weathers and Storms" href="\Weathers and Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Weathers and Storms</a> *
<br><a data-href="Strange Worlds" href="\Strange Worlds" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Strange Worlds</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Traps" href="\Traps" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Traps</a> *
<br><a data-href="Riddles and Puzzles" href="\Riddles and Puzzles" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Riddles and Puzzles</a> *
<br><a data-href="Forbidden Technologies" href="\Forbidden Technologies" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Forbidden Technologies</a> *
<br><a data-href="Crime" href="\Crime" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Crime</a> *
<br><a data-href="Illicit Goods and Services" href="\Illicit Goods and Services" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Illicit Goods and Services</a> *

<br><a data-href="Poison &amp; Venom" href="\Poison &amp; Venom" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Poison &amp; Venom</a> *


<br><a data-href="Disease" href="\Disease" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Disease</a> *
<br><a data-href="Cults" href="\Cults" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cults</a> *
<br>* =  UNDER CONSTRUCTION]]></description><link>table-of-elements.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Table of Elements.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:24:07 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="_attachments\logo.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="_attachments\logo.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Traits]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The Dwarves are an ancestry that shares a common ancestor with Humans and Gnomes, and that has inhabited the mountainous regions of the world for a long while. They have long been and to this day still are largely organised in Clans, a substitute for families.<br><br><br>Dwarves have a short and stocky build, standing shorter than humans, with wide, compact bodies and burly frames. Both male and female dwarves have evolved to grow thick bears that can act as a filter for the rough and dusty air deep within the mountains. Dwarves can live up to around 350 years old, and is considered an adult at the age of 50.<br><br>The murder of one dwarf by another is seen as the most atrocioous and terrible crime a dwarf can commit. For this reason, there is no death sentence among Dwarvenkind. Instead, murderers are exiled.<br><br>Dwarves don't have classic family constructs, and their last names are the names of their clans. Ofte times, within a clan, many dwarves are already related, so dwarves marry and migrate to other clans if they so please. When two dwarves have a child, it is assigned a so-called protector from their clan, because it is believed to be unhealthy for a child to only ever be raised by their own parents. The protector then takes on a lot of the work that comes with raising said child. A clan's bond is very close, and humans often compare them to large families. <br><br>Dwarves believe in a pantheon of gods and have a rich <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Dwarvish Mythology" data-href="Dwarvish Mythology" href="\religions\deities\dwarvish-mythology.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">mythology</a> surrounding them.<br>
In larger cities, priests are usually appointed by the priestly order of their patron god to oversee places of worship. Core values that can be found with any god are good work, and the preservation of ancient dwarvish history.<br><br>Typical foods one would find in dwarven establishments are <a data-href="Ironroot" href="\flora\other\ironroot.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ironroot</a>, goat cheese and bread, the  staples of dwarven food. Living in the mountains, goats are the natural livestock dwarves have domesticated, so goat milk, meat and cheese are the most common ingredients in their cuisine. Ironroot, a native plant to the mountains, chicory, wheat grass and mushrooms even grow underground, and compliment their foods fabulously.<br><br>Dwarves typically introduce themselves by their first name and clan, followed by any titles or honorifics they might have. Their names usually contain hard consonants and typically are 2-3 syllables long.<br><br>First Names<br>
Agna, Bodill, Dolgrin, Edrukk, Grunyar, Ingra, Kazmuk, Kotri, Lupp, Morgrym, Rogar, Rusilka, Torra, Yangrit<br>
Clan Names<br>
Ahnlogryk (meaning "from the mountain's lake."), Padhemvok ("forest-born"), Jarrnryt ("Sunburst"), Elrumarak ("Diamond-made")<br><br>For dwarves, the 50th birthday holds an  important meaning. After fifty years, they cross the boundary to adulthood. While of course every day worth celebrating has a big feast, what makes the 50th special is the ritual that is performed. Every child gets a special, hand-made metal trinket by their protector at birth. At the ritual to adulthood, both the protector and the now adult dwarf will throw their trinkets into a forge, melting the metals down once again to mark the end of their bond, and the beginning of the adult life of the dwarf. The molten metal from the trinket is typically cast into an ingot, and treasured until the young dwarf becomes a protector themselves.<br><br>When dwarves have a disagreement they can not or don't want to settle with words, it results in a duel. Now, a duel must be agreed upon by both fighting parties, and a third neutral one. They will agree on weapons, from fists in unarmed combat to axes and hammers, and how long will be fought. This can be from drawing first blood, from knocking someone unconscious or just off their feet, until someone gives up or even dies.<br>
This is the only legal way for a dwarf to kill another dwarf, but of course it always comes with the risk of being killed yourself.<br>
Duels happen fairly often, though normally they don't go all the way until someone dies. They are fought to settle disagreements, to make out a new leader or find a successor, or just to blow off some steam. <br><br>Hit points: 10<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 20ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Constitution, Wisdom, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Charisma<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-href="Dwarven (Dursk)" href="\languages\dwarven-(dursk).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dwarven (Dursk)</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br>You get one&nbsp;[clan dagger](<a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Weapons.aspx?ID=13" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Weapons.aspx?ID=13</a>&nbsp;of your clan for free, as it was given to you at birth. Selling this dagger is a terrible taboo and earns you the disdain of other dwarves.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=1" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=1</a><br><br><br>In their early history, Dwarves have not yet discovered fire, and they relied on bioluminescent fungi like <a data-href="Glimmercap" href="\flora\fungi\glimmercap.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Glimmercap</a> and other natural light sources to illuminate their tunnels and caves. They also relied on hunting and gathering for their sustenance, although hunting was the more successful way of maintaining their diet.  Eventually, they discovered fire by striking flint against rocks, and it quickly became a valuable resource for warmth, food and metalworking.<br>
With readily available materials all around them, Dwarves became excellent miners, stoneworkers and smiths. As time went on, they carved more and more elaborate homes into the mountainsides and cliff faces. This is also the time, where their first writings emerged.<br>
With the discovery of fire, metalworking and the trade among tribes, Dwarves formed a large community and complex social structure, with rulers and a system of laws. They also established a writing system, at first occurring only on stone tablets, and on their walls.<br><br><br>The ancient city of <a data-href="Hrotmaerahn" href="\Hrotmaerahn" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hrotmaerahn</a> (translated literally to "Old Sky Mountain") was the earliest city to emerge from Dwarvenkind.  During the <a data-href="Era of Storms" href="\Era of Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Storms</a>, Hrotmaerahn began to grow rapidly in population as a bastion against the <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\Highstorms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> that plagued the surface.<br>
The exact founding date of Hrotmaerahn has been lost to time. As it grew, Dwarves began to develop trade relationships outside of the city, with other Dwarven cultures and settlements, exchanging knowledge, valuable metals and Stoneworks for goods and resources. With the discovery of <a data-href="Moonstone" href="\resources\gemstones\moonstone.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moonstone</a>, a gemstone that collects and keeps the moons light within for a considerable amount of time, their advancements into the depths of mountains went even further.<br><br>According to Dwarven legend, the discovery of <a data-href="Runebinding" href="\Runebinding" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Runebinding</a> was a fortunate accident. It is said that a group of Dwarves were exploring the depths of a mountain cave near <a data-href="Hrotmaerahn" href="\Hrotmaerahn" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hrotmaerahn</a> when they came across a peculiar set of glowing symbols etched into the stone. Not knowing what they were, the Dwarves touched the symbols and were immediately infused with magical energy.<br>
Excited by this newfound power, the Dwarves began to experiment with the symbols, carving them into stone and metal and imbuing them with different magical properties. Over time, they discovered that by combining different runes and binding them to anchors, they could create powerful spells that allowed them to do many things like teleporting, or creating powerful wards and enchantments. Yet another growth spurt in the development and history of the Dwarves.<br>
As their mastery of Runebinding grew, so too did their reputation as master craftsmen. They began to craft magical artifacts of immense power.<br>]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\dwarves.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Dwarves.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 14:54:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Appearance]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The Dwarves of Caitha are widely credited with creating the first unified currency in the world, laying the foundation for the economy for centuries to come.<br>
The Dwarven Crown, commonly referred to as just "Crown", the most enduring symbol of trade and wealth. These hexagonal coins, produced in the golden halls of <a data-href="Dhartahl" href="\Dhartahl" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dhartahl</a> have long been the predominant currency used throughout the diverse regions of Caitha.<br><br>Crowns minted in the forges of Dhartahl are hexagonal with a hexagonal hole in the middle. They are approximately 3.5 centimeters in diameter, and have a 5 mm thick border with fine stripes in the middle. Many coins are simple, but some of the golden coins have a symbol printed on them to commemorate an event or important person.<br>
<img alt="goldencrown.png" src="\lib\media\goldencrown.png"><br><br>The copper crown (CC), the silver crown (SC) and the golden crown (GC) are the primary denominations of this currency. 10 Copper Crowns make a silver crown, and 10 silver crowns make a golden crown.<br>
Copper Crowns, often referred to as "Coppers," serve as the basic unit of currency for everyday transactions. Silver Crowns, or "Silvers," are of higher value and commonly used for larger purchases, while Golden Crowns, known as "Goldens," are the most valuable you will encounter in your day to day. There are Platinum coins as well, though they are typically reserved for significant transactions and wealth storage.<br><br>The origins of the Crown can be traced back to the ancient forges of Dhartahl, where Dwarven metallurgists and craftsmen created these hexagonal coins during the <a data-href="Empire Wars" href="\Empire Wars" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Empire Wars</a> in an effort to create an economy that would be much stronger than that of their enemies - with success.<br>
The unification of these coins into a single currency system was a remarkable achievement in a world that had previously relied on a hodgepodge of barter systems and various forms of currency. The Dwarves' reputation for integrity and craftsmanship bolstered the acceptance of their coins among other civilizations.<br>
Centuries have passed since the Dwarven Crowns were first minted, yet they remain the backbone of Caitha's economic stability. The enduring trust in these coins is a testament to the unwavering commitment of the Dwarves to maintain the purity of their currency. Each Crown is carefully casted and pressed in Dhartahl, adhering to the traditional methods passed down through generations.]]></description><link>economics\currency\dwarven-crowns.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Economics/currency/Dwarven Crowns.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 22:45:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\goldencrown.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\goldencrown.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Continents]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The known world consists of four continents, encircled by violent <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\Highstorms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>.<br><img alt="caitha_continents.png" src="\lib\media\caitha_continents.png"><br><br>Kataris is home to climates ranging from wetlands in the east, over temperate, mediterranean and oceanic climates in the center to boreal climates up north. It is rugged and mountainous, and the most diverse as the birthplace of <a data-href="Humans" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\humans.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Humans</a>, <a data-href="Mossin (Halflings)" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\mossin-(halflings).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mossin (Halflings)</a>, <a data-href="Dwarves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\dwarves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dwarves</a> as well as <a data-href="Grippli" href="\Grippli" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Grippli</a>.<br><br>Right south of Kataris, Sutaris is home to hot climates and is dominated by <a data-href="The Red Desert" href="\The Red Desert" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Red Desert</a>, the <a data-href="Iwaîan Desert" href="\Iwaîan Desert" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Iwaîan Desert</a> and the <a data-href="Scorching Highlands" href="\Scorching Highlands" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Scorching Highlands</a>. It is the birthplace of <a data-href="Gnomes" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\gnomes.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Gnomes</a>, and the unlikely home to many others.<br><br>East of Kataris, Antaris is a cold continent with peninsulas, Island chains, and neverending coastlines. It is home to Dwarves, Humans, Elves and <a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a>.<br><br>In the far north, Qador is located at the edge of the Highstorms. It is a cold continent, marked by vast Tundras, Ice and Snow. It is the birthplace of the <a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a>.<br><br>Aroa is at the eastern edge of the known world, right up agains the Highstorms. Not a whole lot is known about it, except for it being the ancestral home of the <a data-href="Elves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\elves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Elves</a>, who can be very secretive.]]></description><link>geographic-elements\continents.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Geographic Elements/Continents.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 09:33:53 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\caitha_continents.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\caitha_continents.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Druidic Sacrifice]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The story of the Druidic Sacrifice is the story of perhaps the single most pivotal and solemn event in the annals of the known world, marking the end of the <a data-href="Era of Storms" href="\Era of Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Storms</a>. <br>In a time before the "<a data-href="Era of Legends" href="\timelines\era-of-legends.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Legends</a>" and the widespread adoption of the <a data-href="Druidic Calendar" href="\Druidic Calendar" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a> that we use today, Mages wielded the extraordinary ability to manipulate the world's weather through a potent form of magic. These wielders of natural forces sought to shape the world's climate, bringing about significant changes that, while awe-inspiring, led to unforeseen and dangerous consequences.<br>The unintended side effect of the Mages' extensive use of magic was the emergence of <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\Highstorms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>. These storms bore little resemblance to conventional storms, replacing lightning flashes with disconcerting moments of darkness and the deep, rolling thunder with high-pitched, eerie sounds.<br>
These storms disrupted the world's natural order and posed a severe threat to all of the known world. Many mages did not realise this, or were simply too hungry for power. Magic users split into two factions, the mighty mages continuing to wield the uncontrollable destructive forces, and the Druids, wanting to save the world from certain doom. They were quick to realize the gravity of their actions, as the number of Highstorms grew uncontrollably, endangering both the physical and metaphysical realms.<br>Brutal magical wars ensued, claiming more lives than we could count today on both sides, but in the end, the Druids emerged victorious.<br>Faced with the dangerous consequences to the degree of manipulation the natural world has seen, the Druid Circles recognized the need for a momentous and collective effort to rectify their past misdeeds. With unity and a deep commitment to protect their world, they embarked on a secretive and large-scale ritual to banish the Highstorms far beyond the borders of the known world.<br>However, this ritual came at an extraordinary cost. Every Druid involved in this endeavour succumbed to exhaustion, marking their sacrifice with their lives.<br>The Druids, who later established the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Time and the Calendar" data-href="Time and the Calendar" href="\timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a>, used this event as its official beginning.<br>Druids today regard the event as a crucial part of their heritage, and they have sworn to preserve Caitha as it is, ensuring the Highstorms remain at bay and refraining from further interference with the world's climate. Every new Druid is brought up with the knowledge that this great sacrifice may one day be required again.<br>In all parts of the world this degree of weather manipulation is outlawed today, and almost everywhere under penalty of death.<br>Nobody really knows what lies beyond the storms that encircle the world, and we may never find out.]]></description><link>historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Historical Elements/Legends and Tales/The Druidic Sacrifice.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 11:41:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Legends and Tales]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Below you can find a list of all currently published Legends and Tales from Caitha. Some consider them folklore, some consider them history. And who knows? Maybe a kernel of truth really lies in some of them.<br>
<br><a data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Druidic Sacrifice</a>
]]></description><link>historical-elements\legends-and-tales.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Historical Elements/Legends and Tales.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 11:42:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Maps]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>In this neat little collection you will (at some point) find all types of maps of Caitha I have created so far.<br>
For now, however, I can only show you this over on worldanvil:<br>
<a rel="noopener" class="external-link" title="eeeeeeee" href="https://www.worldanvil.com/w/caitha-sirnoodle/map/ca56c5e0-50ca-4cd4-9d00-7a8be2a1492c" target="_blank">https://www.worldanvil.com/w/caitha-sirnoodle/map/ca56c5e0-50ca-4cd4-9d00-7a8be2a1492c</a><br><br><br><br><br>]]></description><link>maps\maps.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Maps/Maps.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 15:50:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Time and the Calendar]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A single day on Caitha is roughly the same length as one on Earth. Time is being tracked throughout the day using a combination of sun-positioning, stable candles, water clocks, other mechanical or magical means and - depending on where you live - even using the weather.<br>
Mechanical clocks are technically available, though scarce, not very practical, and incredibly expensive.<br><br>The most widely adapted and established Calendar in Caitha is the <a data-href="Druidic Calendar" href="\Druidic Calendar" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a> - a lunar calendar based on the moon phases of two out of the three <a data-href="Moons" href="\Moons" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moons</a> of Caitha, Elydd, Nevi and Yova, developed by Druids in today's <a data-href="Ilora" href="\Ilora" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ilora</a> based on their observance of the night sky and the seasons.<br>
This Calendar was later adopted and spread through the world through trade and politics by the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Palyra" data-href="Palyra" href="\Palyra" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Palyran Empire</a> during the <a data-href="Era of Legends" href="\timelines\era-of-legends.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Legends</a>. The beginning of this calendar is marked by the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="The Druidic Sacrifice" data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Sacrifice</a>.<br><br>The week is made up of 8 days and based on the blue moon Nevi, which takes 16 days for a full cycle. Every week starts on either a full moon or a new moon on Moonday and goes over firsday, seconday, thirday, fourday, fiveday, sixday, and sevenday.<br><br>A Month on Caitha is made up of 37 days and is based on the white moon Elydd, which takes a full 74 days for a full cycle.  Each new moon for Elydd roughly marks the beginning of a new season.<br>First Bloom<br>
First month of the year, and the arrival of spring. This month celebrates the blossoming of the flora.<br>Goldengrass<br>
Second month of the year, as the sun becomes more intense, this month is marked by an increase in sunlight and warmth leading into summer.<br>Emberfall<br>
Third month of the year, marked by occasional wildfires and dry season in <a data-href="Palyra" href="\Palyra" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Palyra</a>.<br>First Harvest<br>
Fourth month of the year, named after the first harvest that occurs.<br>Seawind<br>
Fifth month of the year, as the winds off the sea become more noticeable, this month signifies the end of summer, and beginning of autumn.<br>Second Harvest<br>
Sixth month of the year, marked by the gathering of resources and another harvest before winter sets in.<br>Sunfade<br>
Seventh month of the year, as the sun fades and rainy season sets in, this month is marked by abundant coastal precipitation.<br>Mistrend<br>
Eighth month of the year, characterised by the season's capacity to shroud and renew the land.<br><br>A full year on Caitha takes 296 days, or 8 months. Every season is roughly two months long.]]></description><link>timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Timelines/Time and the Calendar.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 15:57:50 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>