<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[A Long Story]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib\media\favicon.png</url><title>A Long Story</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 16:35:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib\rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 16:35:22 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Mountain Ram]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Infobox

<img alt="ram.png" src="\lib\media\ram.png"><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="ram.png" data-href="ram.png" href="\_attachments\ram.png" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">show image</a>


<br><br>Mountain Rams are robust, quadrupedal creatures with impressive physique and a majestic air. Their sturdy bodies are covered in dense, coarse fur, which serves as insulation against the biting mountain winds. They sport formidable, spiral-shaped horns that arc from their foreheads, the tips often sharpened naturally through rigorous mountain-climbing and butting contests. These powerful creatures stand about five feet tall at the shoulder and can grow up to nine feet in length, from nose to tail.<br><br>Mountain Rams are exclusively found in the high-altitude regions of Caitha, primarily inhabiting the lofty crags and precipices of the formidable mountain ranges. Their remarkable adaptation to these extreme environments allows them to traverse near-vertical cliffs and precipitous slopes with ease.<br><br>These creatures are known for their sure-footedness and agility, allowing them to navigate treacherous terrains with grace. They often form tight-knit herds led by a dominant male, while the females, known as ewes, protect the young. Mountain Rams are known for their playful butting contests, a way to establish dominance within the herd.<br><br>Their diet mainly consists of hardy mountain vegetation such as lichens, mosses, <a data-href="Ironroot" href="\flora\other\ironroot.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ironroot</a>, and tough alpine shrubs. They also consume mineral-rich stones, which not only provide essential nutrients but also aid in the grinding down of their ever-growing horns.<br><br>Breeding typically occurs during the spring when the high-altitude meadows are carpeted with fresh vegetation. After a gestation period of about six months, the ewes give birth to a single lamb, which is guarded diligently within the protective confines of the herd.<br><br>Mountain Rams hold deep cultural significance for the Dwarves of Caitha. They are regarded as symbols of endurance, resilience, and the indomitable spirit of the mountain dwellers. The dwarves have adopted the Mountain Rams as trusted companions, employing them for transportation through the rugged terrain and even into battle.<br><br>Dwarves have harnessed the strength and agility of Mountain Rams for centuries, using them as formidable mounts in both times of war and peaceful journeys through the treacherous mountains. These highly domesticated creatures have become an integral part of Dwarven culture, providing not only transportation but a deep emotional connection.<br><br>While Mountain Rams are formidable and well-equipped to defend themselves, they do face threats in their alpine homes. Fearsome predators like the <a data-href="Frostwyrm" href="\fauna\other\frostwyrm.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Frostwyrm</a> and <a data-href="Mountaindragon" href="\fauna\other\mountaindragon.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mountaindragon</a> occasionally target them, seeking to make a meal of these hardy herbivores. Dwarves have learned to safeguard their prized steeds, often embarking on perilous missions to eliminate these threats and ensure the continued existence of their beloved Mountain Rams.<br>
<img alt="ram 2.png" src="\lib\media\ram-2.png">]]></description><link>fauna\mammals\mountain-ram.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Fauna/Mammals/Mountain Ram.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 16:13:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\ram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\ram.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mountain Ram]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Infobox

<img alt="ram.png" src="\lib\media\ram.png"><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="ram.png" data-href="ram.png" href="\_attachments\ram.png" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">show image</a>


<br><br>Mountain Rams are robust, quadrupedal creatures with impressive physique and a majestic air. Their sturdy bodies are covered in dense, coarse fur, which serves as insulation against the biting mountain winds. They sport formidable, spiral-shaped horns that arc from their foreheads, the tips often sharpened naturally through rigorous mountain-climbing and butting contests. These powerful creatures stand about five feet tall at the shoulder and can grow up to nine feet in length, from nose to tail.<br><br>Mountain Rams are exclusively found in the high-altitude regions of Caitha, primarily inhabiting the lofty crags and precipices of the formidable mountain ranges. Their remarkable adaptation to these extreme environments allows them to traverse near-vertical cliffs and precipitous slopes with ease.<br><br>These creatures are known for their sure-footedness and agility, allowing them to navigate treacherous terrains with grace. They often form tight-knit herds led by a dominant male, while the females, known as ewes, protect the young. Mountain Rams are known for their playful butting contests, a way to establish dominance within the herd.<br><br>Their diet mainly consists of hardy mountain vegetation such as lichens, mosses, <a data-href="Ironroot" href="\flora\other\ironroot.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ironroot</a>, and tough alpine shrubs. They also consume mineral-rich stones, which not only provide essential nutrients but also aid in the grinding down of their ever-growing horns.<br><br>Breeding typically occurs during the spring when the high-altitude meadows are carpeted with fresh vegetation. After a gestation period of about six months, the ewes give birth to a single lamb, which is guarded diligently within the protective confines of the herd.<br><br>Mountain Rams hold deep cultural significance for the Dwarves of Caitha. They are regarded as symbols of endurance, resilience, and the indomitable spirit of the mountain dwellers. The dwarves have adopted the Mountain Rams as trusted companions, employing them for transportation through the rugged terrain and even into battle.<br><br>Dwarves have harnessed the strength and agility of Mountain Rams for centuries, using them as formidable mounts in both times of war and peaceful journeys through the treacherous mountains. These highly domesticated creatures have become an integral part of Dwarven culture, providing not only transportation but a deep emotional connection.<br><br>While Mountain Rams are formidable and well-equipped to defend themselves, they do face threats in their alpine homes. Fearsome predators like the <a data-href="Frostwyrm" href="\fauna\other\frostwyrm.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Frostwyrm</a> and <a data-href="Mountaindragon" href="\fauna\other\mountaindragon.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mountaindragon</a> occasionally target them, seeking to make a meal of these hardy herbivores. Dwarves have learned to safeguard their prized steeds, often embarking on perilous missions to eliminate these threats and ensure the continued existence of their beloved Mountain Rams.<br>
<img alt="ram 2.png" src="\lib\media\ram-2.png">]]></description><link>fauna\mountain-ram-1.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Fauna/Mountain Ram 1.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 16:13:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\ram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\ram.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Continents]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The known world consists of four continents, encircled by violent <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>.<br><img alt="caitha_continents.png" src="\lib\media\caitha_continents.png"><br><br>Kataris is home to climates ranging from wetlands in the east, over temperate, mediterranean and oceanic climates in the center to boreal climates up north. It is rugged and mountainous, and the most diverse as the birthplace of <a data-href="Humans" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\humans.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Humans</a>, <a data-href="Mossin (Halflings)" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\mossin-(halflings).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mossin (Halflings)</a>, <a data-href="Dwarves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\dwarves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dwarves</a> as well as <a data-href="Grippli" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\grippli.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Grippli</a>.<br><br>Right south of Kataris, Sutaris is home to hot climates and is dominated by <a data-href="The Red Desert" href="\The Red Desert" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Red Desert</a>, the <a data-href="Iwaîan Desert" href="\Iwaîan Desert" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Iwaîan Desert</a> and the <a data-href="Scorching Highlands" href="\Scorching Highlands" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Scorching Highlands</a>. It is the birthplace of <a data-href="Gnomes" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\gnomes.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Gnomes</a>, <a data-href="Goblins" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\goblins.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Goblins</a>, and the unlikely home to many others.<br><br>East of Kataris, Antaris is a cold continent with peninsulas, Island chains, and neverending coastlines. It is home to Dwarves, Humans, Elves and <a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a>.<br><br>In the far north, Qador is located at the edge of the Highstorms. It is a cold continent, marked by vast Tundras, Ice and Snow. It is home to the <a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a>.<br><br>Aroa is at the eastern edge of the known world, right up agains the Highstorms. Not a whole lot is known about it, except for it being the ancestral home of the <a data-href="Elves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\elves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Elves</a>, who can be very secretive.]]></description><link>geographic-elements\continents.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Geographic Elements/Continents.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 13:28:05 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\caitha_continents.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\caitha_continents.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Automatons]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Intelligent constructs housing actual souls, a blend of technological ingenuity and immense magical power.<br><br><br>Automatons share a common construction—a blend of magically treated metals and stone. This design allows automatons to withstand the rigors of direct combat and makes them particularly hardy. Their appearance varies depending on the needs of its role. Most automatons have a basic humanoid shape, though some instead have shapes that closely resemble animals. The majority of automatons have a single eye that glows with a dim, magical light. Each also contains a powerful artifact that both houses its individual soul and uses a combination of life and planar energy for power. These&nbsp;automaton cores&nbsp;are marvels of magical engineering whose method of creation has been lost to time.<br>As constructs, automatons typically don't need to breathe, eat, or sleep; however, the body of an automaton needs to vent an imperceivable magical exhaust at a constant rate. This venting process requires breathable air to prevent a buildup of exhaust that can clog the automaton's systems, sometimes to fatal effect. Thus, automatons can still suffocate much like living creatures. Though they don't sleep, automatons require a period of magical recalibration and restoration which stabilizes the energies within their core. Without this process, an&nbsp;automaton core&nbsp;is incapable of fully powering the automaton and they enter an inefficient state (similar to a humanoid who doesn't get 8 hours of sleep).  <br>Automatons don't age and the design of their cores grants them a seemingly endless power source. Many automatons that exist today are hundreds of years old, their bodies as efficient as the day of their creation, even if their minds might have deteriorated with the strain of the ages. Automatons lost over time typically met violent ends. An automaton's body is just as vulnerable to destruction as any other construct, though destroying an&nbsp;automaton core&nbsp;is more difficult. As such, an automaton's soul might remain trapped within its core for years after the destruction of its body. This was the intent of the original creators, who hoped to provide functional immortality. <br>In some cases, an automaton can learn how to consciously or subconsciously influence its core. These automatons eventually learn how to release their souls from their cores, allowing their souls to move on when they feel they have achieved a satisfying life. This act leaves the automaton as a mindless construct, typically still active but no longer capable of anything but aimless wandering and occasional acts of self-defense.<br><br>Due to their rarity, Automatons don't have a society of their own. There are few cases of Automatons originally designed to work together who still do so, but those are few and far between. There are no Automaton settlements in the known world, so they are far more likely to encounter other ancestries.<br>
Many who became automatons had some role in society prior to their transformation, and often gravitate toward lives that best represent these roles, even if they no longer remember their former lives.<br><br>The method of creating sentient automatons is incredibly difficult to perform and takes immense power. As such, encountering one that is not a mindless machine is rare.<br><br>Since an Automaton contains a sentient beings soul, their religion or lack thereof depends entirely on who inhabits the Automaton core, though they tend to worship gods of technology or magic.<br><br>Automaton Names are as varied as the souls that inhibit them when they keep the name they had before their transformation, if they can even remember it. <br><br>Automatons are built to receive enhancements and modifications to their bodies. Many automaton ancestry feats have an "Enhancement" line that represents a possible augmentation you can acquire. You don't gain the benefits of the enhancement unless you take a feat that grants you those benefits, such as Lesser Augmentation. You can only gain the enhancements of a given feat once.<br><br>Mechanically, Automatons are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 8<br>
Size: Medium or Small<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Strength, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: None<br><br>You speak, read and write Common and <a data-href="Utopian" href="\Utopian" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Utopian</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br>Your body contains an&nbsp;automaton core&nbsp;infused with planar quintessence that grants you power to perform various tasks and houses your soul and life energy. This life energy flows through you much like the blood of humanoids. As a result, you are a living creature. You don't have the typical&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=35" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=35" target="_blank">construct</a>&nbsp;immunities, can be affected by effects that target a living creature, and can recover Hit Points normally via&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=128" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=128" target="_blank">positive</a>&nbsp;energy. Additionally, you are not destroyed when reduced to 0 Hit Points. Instead, your life energy attempts to keep you active even in dire straits; you are&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=38" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=38" target="_blank">knocked out</a>&nbsp;and begin&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=11" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=11" target="_blank">dying</a>&nbsp;when reduced to 0 Hit Points.<br><br>Your physiological needs are different than those of living creatures. You don't need to eat or drink. You don't need to sleep, but you still need a daily period of rest. During this period of rest, you must enter a recuperating standby state for 2 hours, which is similar to sleeping except you are aware of your surroundings and don't take penalties for being&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=38" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=38" target="_blank">unconscious</a>. Much like with sleeping, if you go too long without entering your standby state, you become&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=15" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=15" target="_blank">fatigued</a>&nbsp;and can't recover until you enter standby for 2 hours.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=48" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=48</a>]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\automatons.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Automatons.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 10:37:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fleshwarps]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Fleshwarps are people whose forms were created or radically transformed by magic, alchemy, or unnatural energies. Their unorthodox appearance can make it difficult for them to find a place for themselves in the world.<br>
Fleshwarps are those who have been permanently altered by such methods—sometimes a sapient being created whole cloth from inanimate flesh, but often a victim unwillingly transformed by strange energies or sadistic creators.<br>
The ancestry name “fleshwarp” is an umbrella term, since the actual fleshwarping process is more infamously well-known than are alterations caused by uncontrolled magic, technology, or fringe science. Whether practiced by Wizards, Alchemists or Scientists, fleshwarping is the craft of reshaping flesh and mind in vats of foul magical reagents. This has led some scholars of monsters to argue that only those beings created by traditional fleshwarping should be considered fleshwarps. Regardless of the source of their altered forms, fleshwarps bear their new shape forever, transformed beings living a wild and strange existence beyond what was possible for their original ancestry.<br><br><br>Fleshwarps are humanoids, ranging from 5 to 7 feet tall and from just under 100 pounds to more than 300 pounds. The proportion and appearance of their limbs and features differ widely, but fleshwarps functionally have two legs, two arms, and a single head; a fleshwarp with more limbs than this should consider an appropriate ancestry feat to reflect this variance, or one of their limbs might be vestigial and mostly nonfunctional. Fleshwarps differ widely in their appearance due to the unique circumstances of their creation. Even fleshwarp siblings or two people transformed through the same procedure might look wildly different.<br><br>Fleshwarps live on the margins of society. The need to defend themselves drives them to distrust crowds or peiple in general. Fleshwarps are few in number, and congregations of them are rare. They choose lives that allow them to avoid contact with people who might fear or persecute them.<br>
Fleshwarps value endurance and are quick to learn from others, so those who come into contact with others of their kind usually share stories that help each other survive, hide, or thrive more effectively. How a fleshwarp formed can be a painful or horrifying subject, one they consider rude to discuss with anyone besides close friends or loved ones.<br>
Although bigoted or short-sighted people view fleshwarps as monsters, fleshwarps are no more or less prone to evil than any other people, and most seek only to live their lives without trouble.<br><br>Fleshwarps can come from any culture or ancestry, so they may have very varied names. However, some give themselves new names after being transformed, whether to celebrate the change, recognize a new phase of their lives, or conceal their past identity. They may also carry a descriptive nickname granted to them by others.<br><br>Mechanically, Fleshwarps are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 10<br>
Size: Medium or Small<br>
Speed: 25 feet<br>
Ability Boosts: Constitution, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: None<br><br>You speak, read and write Common and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br>Your unorthodox body resists physical afflictions meant for other creatures. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saves against&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=46" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=46" target="_blank">diseases</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=126" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=126" target="_blank">poisons</a>.<br><br>Fleshwarps have a variety of reasons for taking up the life of an adventurer. Some are turned out of their homes by an uncaring parent or a suspicious mob. Other fleshwarps travel to learn more about their own transformation or to seek out others of their kind. A few even actively seek the means—either technological or magical—to undo their transformations or adopt a new form that won't incite repulsion or fear in common people. Still others understand that a good way to earn respect is to solve a community's problems—then quickly leave the area—and therefore fall into the role of itinerant adventurers-for-hire.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=31" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=31</a>]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\fleshwarps.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Fleshwarps.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 10:53:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Leshy]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Leshies are immortal spirits of nature temporarily granted physical forms. As guardians and emissaries of the environment, leshies are “born” when a skilled druid or other master of magic conducts a ritual to create a suitable vessel, and then a spirit chooses that vessel to be their temporary home. Leshies are self-sufficient from the moment the ritual ends, though it isn't uncommon for leshies to maintain lifelong bonds with their creators. Many leshies relish the opportunity to interact with the physical world. While most leshy spirits are ancient, they rarely recall past lifetimes and see their new life as a chance to experience the wonders of the world once more.<br><br><br>Leshies are as varied as the material used to create their vessels, sometimes appearing as a bizarre mishmash of various plants or fungi. Their bodies are vaguely humanoid in shape, with numerous characteristics of the plant or fungus from which they were made. A typical leshy is about 3 feet tall. Leshies begin their lives as adults and don't age.<br><br>To most leshies, the concept of family is not a matter of birth, but rather determined by bonds of loyalty and friendship. Leshies are dedicated allies, but they have little tolerance for those who would despoil nature.<br>
Leshies' genders are determined by the spirits that inhabit their bodies. Some leshies are exclusively male or female, while many consider themselves both. Others, particularly fungus leshies, tend toward far more complex expressions of gender, or eschew the concept entirely. <br><br>Leshies choose and change their names multiple times throughout their lives.<br><br>Scarlet in Summer, Verdant Taleweaver, Lurking Hunter, Masterful Sun Drinker, Noon Sky Evening Song, Snowy Pine Branch, Cascading Rapids<br><br>Mechanically, Leshies are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 8<br>
Size: Small<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Constitution, Wisdom, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Intelligence<br><br>You speak, read and write Common, Fey and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br>You gain nourishment in the same way that the plants or fungi that match your body type normally do, through some combination of photosynthesis, absorbing minerals with your roots, or scavenging decaying matter. You typically do not need to pay for food. If you normally rely on photosynthesis and go without sunlight for 1 week, you begin to&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Rules.aspx?ID=537" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Rules.aspx?ID=537" target="_blank">starve</a>. You can derive nourishment from specially formulated bottles of sunlight instead of natural sunlight, but these bottles cost 10 times as much as standard rations (or 40 sp).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=65" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=65</a>]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\leshy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Leshy.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 10:59:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Poppets]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Poppets are small, basic constructs that typically help their owners with simple tasks. Occasionally, poppets gain sapience, independence, and a spark of life. Elevated beyond mere helpers or playthings, these poppets are free to chart their own destinies.<br>
Most commonly made of cloth, wicker, and wood, poppets are among the simplest of constructs. They serve as helpers to fetch tools, clean dishes, tidy rooms, or perform other light tasks. Their size and appearance vary, but nearly all poppets appear humanoid in shape and between 1 to 3 feet tall. Wealthy families sometimes purchase poppets as toys, with their squishy bodies and stitched smiles, to keep their children company. Most poppets can't speak and lack the intellect to understand speech beyond preprogrammed orders. Poppets can become familiars, as presented&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Familiars.aspx?Specific=true&amp;ID=7" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Familiars.aspx?Specific=true&amp;ID=7" target="_blank">here</a>.<br>Very, very rarely, a common poppet spontaneously manifests a spark of life—a tiny bit of life essence— and becomes a thinking, independent creature. These events are exceedingly rare; fewer than one in a thousand gain this spark. A poppet might manifest this life essence through a magical fluke in its construction, a brush with ephemeral spirits, or even the fervent wish of a loving child. Whatever their origin, the poppets described here as an ancestry have their own life and free will. They might consider their creators or former owners to be friends, but they acknowledge no one as their master and often leave comfortable homes or workshops to seek their place in the world.<br>
Sapient living poppets usually refer to themselves as “awakened” to indicate the moment they gained clear and true self-awareness. Poppets might talk about this event as the time they “popped up,” “woke up,” or “sparked alive.” Most poppets celebrate two special anniversaries each year: the day of their initial creation (which, for most poppets, they must learn secondhand or by studying their creator's records) and the day they awoke to true consciousness.<br><br><br>Living poppets are both humanoids and constructs, which gives them some of the benefits and drawbacks of each category. Their bodies are usually made of wood and wicker, but they can be made of cloth, leather, tin, stuffing, or delicate clockwork. Either way, poppets burn or melt quickly and must take care to avoid fire. They virtually never look alike, as each is created from unique and unusual circumstances. They're usually roughly made with button eyes sewn onto blank faces, strings of yarn in place of hair, and a simple dress or tunic made from coarse, cheap cloth.<br>
Poppets are fully alert and self-aware when they awaken to sentience; although they might not know much at first, they instantly gain intelligence and consciousness. They must breathe and sleep, and they must consume food and water each day; through a sort of magical digestion they can restore rips, tears, or scuffs in their physical form. Poppets don't age the same way fleshy creatures do, but they slowly wear down in physical form as well as in mental acuity. A poppet that tends to their body and mind (and takes care to avoid fire) can live up to 30 years.<br><br>Free-willed poppets are so rare that almost no such poppet has met another. Poppets normally live with larger creatures, though not always their creators, and tend to get along well in societies sized for larger creatures. Most live in cities because that's where toy makers, clockwork crafters, and other specialists have their shops, but poppets created by lonely hermits or reclusive inventors might prefer a life in the wilderness.<br>
Poppets often stay on the lookout for other creatures who, like them, have stumbled into self-awareness. They might have regular conversations with animated objects, golems, houseplants, statues, or toys, in which they're deeply polite out of a desire to leave a good impression for the time when the object “wakes up.”<br>Awakened poppets tend to retain their drive to aid others. They're generally good, and more poppets are lawful than chaotic. Some spend their time trying to uncover secrets of their creation, find others like them, or keep out of trouble.<br><br>Poppets aren't typically religious, unless a particular faith defined their creation, such as being made from scraps of altar cloth or woven from sacred plant matter. These poppets tend to be vocally religious.<br><br>Poppets generally choose their own names, usually descriptive nicknames based on their materials, patterns, size, or demeanor. They tend to pick up and shed nicknames throughout their lives, and they happily adopt nicknames given to them by people they like. A poppet fashioned to look like a particular person, such as a doll sewn to resemble a deceased child, might proudly take the name of that person.<br><br>Burlap, Buttoneyes, Checker, Clockwhirr, Fivestitch, Nettle, Scramble, Stuffing, Taffeta, Tattercap<br><br>Mechanically, BLANK are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 6<br>
Size: Small<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Constitution, Charisma, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Dexterity<br><br>You speak, read and write Common, as well as additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br>The materials of your body resist ailments that assail the flesh. You gain a +1 circumstance bonus to saving throws against&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=40" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=40" target="_blank">death</a>&nbsp;effects,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=46" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=46" target="_blank">disease</a>, and&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=126" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=126" target="_blank">poison</a>&nbsp;as well as to saving throws against effects that would give you the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=10" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=10" target="_blank">drained</a>,&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=28" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=28" target="_blank">paralyzed</a>, or&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=34" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=34" target="_blank">sickened</a>&nbsp;conditions. Your spark of life means that you're a living creature, and you can be healed by positive energy and harmed by negative energy as normal.<br><br>You have weakness to&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=72" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=72" target="_blank">fire</a>&nbsp;damage equal to one-third your level (minimum 1).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=49" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=49</a><br><br><br>Nearly all poppets are interested in helping others and finding more creatures like themselves, and both these motivations are excellent for adventure. Yet, a poppet might have any number of other, more personal motives. A poppet might adventure to find a cure for a terminally ill creator, carry out the dying wish of a deceased friend, or complete the life's goal of a spirit that awakened within them, even if the poppet doesn't know who that person was in life. A poppet might take up arms to rescue kidnapped friends or save endangered children. Poppets aren't often greedy, but some might adventure to adorn their simple forms with gemstone eyes, golden thread, or other flashy accoutrements.<br><br>Poppets don't often meet another of their kind, much less settle down together. Poppet-only settlements simply don't exist or are so remote as to be wholly unknown. Instead, poppets are most common in large cities, surrounded by the bustle of crowds. Any place where people appreciate skilled artisans, whether in cloth or clockworks, is a good place to find simple poppets, and thus awakened poppets are more likely to be found in bigger cities. Poppets usually have a network of allies to draw upon in their communities; for many poppets, this network includes their creator and their creator's associates, but even poppets who don't know their creator tend to make themselves useful and liked.<br><br>It might seem strange to picture a poppet walking into a general store to buy rope and jerky, but such occurrences aren't uncommon in urban areas. Poppets are, after all, designed to handle mundane tasks, so people aren't likely to call attention to a poppet going about routine business in such communities. People might even help the poppet out by leaning a plank so it can reach a counter or adjusting a heavy load—thinking that, by doing so, they're aiding a powerful or influential owner. Talk is likely to circulate, however, if the poppet is active in a small settlement where such helper constructs are unknown, or if the poppet is engaged in some truly unusual tasks, like giving a speech or dragging in a slain monster for a bounty.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\poppets.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Poppets.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 11:33:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Vanara]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
Vanaras, nimble and spirited, small in stature but vast in spirit, they darted through the canopy with such ease, it was as if the very trees had come alive.

<br>from "Among the Canopies: Studying the Vanaras", by Captain Elara Morn, 254 EoL

<br><br><br>Vanaras are inquisitive and mischievous monkey-like humanoids with short, soft fur, expressive eyes, and long, prehensile tails. Their handlike feet and agile builds serve them well in the jungles of <a data-href="Tangara" href="\Tangara" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Tangara</a> where most Vanaras live.<br>
They're rarely much taller than 5 feet, but they usually look smaller because of their slight, nimble builds. Vanaras are covered with a thin layer of soft fur over their entire bodies. This fur can be tan, brown, or golden and rarely has spots or stripes. The hair on a vanara's head grows thicker and more luxurious; it's easy to arrange into elaborate hairstyles, and many vanaras like to do so. This hair is nearly always of the same color as the vanara's body fur, with the exception of rare “whitecape” vanaras with manes of fine, pale hair, who might be born into any vanara family. Vanaras have large, expressive eyes and mouths with blunt teeth and pointed incisors. Vanaras are adults at 13 years old and usually live about 60 years.<br><br>Vanaras are tricksters who love pranks, but they temper this tendency toward mischief with good intentions and a love of their community—however they personally define that community. They're rarely agitators or troublemakers simply for the sake of causing chaos; they do so to encourage humility among the inflexible or humorless. Most vanaras are mindful of the virtues necessary to elevate their immortal souls and try to act accordingly. Vanaras are thus most likely to be neutral good.<br><br>Vanaras practice a form of animism, revering the spirits of the jungle that they call the "Voices of Tangara." They believe these spirits inhabit every tree, vine, and stream, guiding and watching over the Vanaras. Their rituals often involve elaborate dances and music, believed to please these spirits and ensure the tribe's safety and prosperity. Key ceremonies coincide with lunar phases, which they believe are times when the veil between their world and the spirit world is thinnest.<br><br>The Vanaran cuisine primarily consists of fruits, nuts, and leaves, supplemented by insects and small reptiles. Food is often eaten fresh, though they also have methods of preservation mainly involving drying and smoking.<br><br>Newborn vanaras aren't given names other than descriptors of their infant personalities or habits, like “Grip-Hand” or “Wailer.” When they learn to speak, vanaras are given another name based on important historical or mythological figures, or they're given the name of a specific ancestor they resemble in appearance or attitude (or whom their community hopes they'll grow to resemble). The chosen name usually contains consonants or vowels the young vanara frequently uses, as vanaras don't see a lot of use in giving someone a name they can't easily pronounce.<br><br>Ashpaka, Chichipi, Haangeno, Hasa, Huanu, Kana, Nammem, Roprutu, Thathona, Unulu, Vivatu<br><br>Mechanically, Vanara are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 6<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Dexterity, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: None<br><br>You speak, read and write Common and <a data-href="Vanara (Language)" href="\Vanara (Language)" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Vanara (Language)</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=55" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=55</a><br><br><br>Vanaras have always lived in tribes, roaming the jungles of Tangara in search of food. Their early culture was marked by a deep connection to their environment and the 4 main Islands they called home. Vanaras are skilled climbers and hunters, using their agility to gather resources from the treetops. They were quick to invent their own form of seafaring to move between their tropical Island homes.<br><br>The Era of Storms brought significant challenges to the Vanaras. The intense weather patterns and frequent storms tested their resilience and adaptability. Many tribes moved deeper into the jungles, developing more sophisticated methods of building shelters and gathering food that could withstand the harsh conditions. It was during this time that the Vanaras refined their techniques in weaving and woodwork, crafting homes that swayed with the trees during storms rather than succumbing to the wind and rain.<br><br>Emerging from the Era of Storms, the Vanaras entered the Era of Legends with a renewed sense of community and purpose. They began to establish more permanent settlements, which evolved into intricate treetop villages connected by bridges and platforms. The isolation of their island home allowed them to develop a unique culture largely unaffected by outside influences.<br>As explorers and traders eventually discovered Tangara, the Vanaras were cautious but curious about these new visitors. Over time, they began to trade with the outside world, exchanging exotic jungle products for goods and ideas that were previously unknown to them. This contact enriched Vanara culture, introducing them to new technologies and beliefs, yet they remained deeply rooted in their traditions and values.<br>Today, the Vanaras are known for their vibrant communities and rich cultural heritage. They continue to live in harmony with the jungle, respecting the spirits of Tangara while slowly embracing the opportunities and challenges of a broader world.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\vanara.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Vanara.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 10:17:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Ancestries]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>All the inhabitants of Caitha, as far as we know, are part of one of the following sapient species:<br>
If you find something on <a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/</a> that you don't find listed here but really want to play, talk to your GM, maybe you can figure something out together.<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Dwarves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\dwarves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dwarves</a>
<br><a data-href="Elves" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\elves.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Elves</a>
<br><a data-href="Gnomes" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\gnomes.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Gnomes</a>
<br><a data-href="Goblins" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\goblins.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Goblins</a>
<br><a data-href="Humans" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\humans.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Humans</a>
<br><a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a>
<br><a data-href="Orcs" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\orcs.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Orcs</a>
<br><a data-href="Mossin (Halflings)" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\mossin-(halflings).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mossin (Halflings)</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Grippli" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\grippli.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Grippli</a>
<br><a data-href="Lizardfolk" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\lizardfolk.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Lizardfolk</a>
<br><a data-href="Vanara" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\vanara.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Vanara</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Automatons" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\automatons.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Automatons</a>
<br><a data-href="Fleshwarps" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\fleshwarps.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fleshwarps</a>
<br><a data-href="Leshy" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\leshy.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Leshy</a>
<br><a data-href="Poppets" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\poppets.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Poppets</a>
]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 11:33:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dwarves]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The Dwarves are an ancestry that shares a common ancestor with Humans and Gnomes, and that has inhabited the mountainous regions of the world for a long while. They have long been and to this day still are largely organised in Clans, a substitute for families.<br><br><br>Dwarves have a short and stocky build, standing shorter than humans, with wide, compact bodies and burly frames. Both male and female dwarves have evolved to grow thick bears that can act as a filter for the rough and dusty air deep within the mountains. Dwarves can live up to around 350 years old, and is considered an adult at the age of 50.<br><br>The murder of one dwarf by another is seen as the most atrocioous and terrible crime a dwarf can commit. For this reason, there is no death sentence among Dwarvenkind. Instead, murderers are exiled.<br><br>Dwarves don't have classic family constructs, and their last names are the names of their clans. Ofte times, within a clan, many dwarves are already related, so dwarves marry and migrate to other clans if they so please. When two dwarves have a child, it is assigned a so-called protector from their clan, because it is believed to be unhealthy for a child to only ever be raised by their own parents. The protector then takes on a lot of the work that comes with raising said child. A clan's bond is very close, and humans often compare them to large families. <br><br>Dwarves believe in a pantheon of gods and have a rich <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Dwarvish Mythology" data-href="Dwarvish Mythology" href="\religions\deities\dwarvish-mythology.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">mythology</a> surrounding them.<br>
In larger cities, priests are usually appointed by the priestly order of their patron god to oversee places of worship. Core values that can be found with any god are good work, and the preservation of ancient dwarvish history.<br><br>Typical foods one would find in dwarven establishments are <a data-href="Ironroot" href="\flora\other\ironroot.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ironroot</a>, goat cheese and bread, the  staples of dwarven food. Living in the mountains, goats are the natural livestock dwarves have domesticated, so goat milk, meat and cheese are the most common ingredients in their cuisine. Ironroot, a native plant to the mountains, chicory, wheat grass and mushrooms even grow underground, and compliment their foods fabulously.<br><br>Dwarves typically introduce themselves by their first name and clan, followed by any titles or honorifics they might have. Their names usually contain hard consonants and typically are 2-3 syllables long.<br><br>First Names<br>
Agna, Bodill, Dolgrin, Edrukk, Grunyar, Ingra, Kazmuk, Kotri, Lupp, Morgrym, Rogar, Rusilka, Torra, Yangrit<br>
Clan Names<br>
Ahnlogryk (meaning "from the mountain's lake."), Padhemvok ("forest-born"), Jarrnryt ("Sunburst"), Elrumarak ("Diamond-made")<br><br>For dwarves, the 50th birthday holds an  important meaning. After fifty years, they cross the boundary to adulthood. While of course every day worth celebrating has a big feast, what makes the 50th special is the ritual that is performed. Every child gets a special, hand-made metal trinket by their protector at birth. At the ritual to adulthood, both the protector and the now adult dwarf will throw their trinkets into a forge, melting the metals down once again to mark the end of their bond, and the beginning of the adult life of the dwarf. The molten metal from the trinket is typically cast into an ingot, and treasured until the young dwarf becomes a protector themselves.<br><br>When dwarves have a disagreement they can not or don't want to settle with words, it results in a duel. Now, a duel must be agreed upon by both fighting parties, and a third neutral one. They will agree on weapons, from fists in unarmed combat to axes and hammers, and how long will be fought. This can be from drawing first blood, from knocking someone unconscious or just off their feet, until someone gives up or even dies.<br>
This is the only legal way for a dwarf to kill another dwarf, but of course it always comes with the risk of being killed yourself.<br>
Duels happen fairly often, though normally they don't go all the way until someone dies. They are fought to settle disagreements, to make out a new leader or find a successor, or just to blow off some steam. <br><br>Mechanically, Dwarves are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 10<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 20ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Constitution, Wisdom, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Charisma<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-href="Dwarven (Dursk)" href="\languages\dwarven-(dursk).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dwarven (Dursk)</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br>You get one&nbsp;[clan dagger](<a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Weapons.aspx?ID=13" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Weapons.aspx?ID=13</a>&nbsp;of your clan for free, as it was given to you at birth. Selling this dagger is a terrible taboo and earns you the disdain of other dwarves.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=1" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=1</a><br><br><br>In their early history, Dwarves have not yet discovered fire, and they relied on bioluminescent fungi like <a data-href="Glimmercap" href="\flora\fungi\glimmercap.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Glimmercap</a> and other natural light sources to illuminate their tunnels and caves. They also relied on hunting and gathering for their sustenance, although hunting was the more successful way of maintaining their diet.  Eventually, they discovered fire by striking flint against rocks, and it quickly became a valuable resource for warmth, food and metalworking.<br>
With readily available materials all around them, Dwarves became excellent miners, stoneworkers and smiths. As time went on, they carved more and more elaborate homes into the mountainsides and cliff faces. This is also the time, where their first writings emerged.<br>
With the discovery of fire, metalworking and the trade among tribes, Dwarves formed a large community and complex social structure, with rulers and a system of laws. They also established a writing system, at first occurring only on stone tablets, and on their walls.<br><br><br>The ancient city of <a data-href="Hrotmaerahn" href="\Hrotmaerahn" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hrotmaerahn</a> (translated literally to "Old Sky Mountain") was the earliest city to emerge from Dwarvenkind.  During the <a data-href="Era of Storms" href="\Era of Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Storms</a>, Hrotmaerahn began to grow rapidly in population as a bastion against the <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> that plagued the surface.<br>
The exact founding date of Hrotmaerahn has been lost to time. As it grew, Dwarves began to develop trade relationships outside of the city, with other Dwarven cultures and settlements, exchanging knowledge, valuable metals and Stoneworks for goods and resources. With the discovery of <a data-href="Moonstone" href="\resources\gemstones\moonstone.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moonstone</a>, a gemstone that collects and keeps the moons light within for a considerable amount of time, their advancements into the depths of mountains went even further.<br><br>According to Dwarven legend, the discovery of <a data-href="Runebinding" href="\Runebinding" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Runebinding</a> was a fortunate accident. It is said that a group of Dwarves were exploring the depths of a mountain cave near <a data-href="Hrotmaerahn" href="\Hrotmaerahn" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hrotmaerahn</a> when they came across a peculiar set of glowing symbols etched into the stone. Not knowing what they were, the Dwarves touched the symbols and were immediately infused with magical energy.<br>
Excited by this newfound power, the Dwarves began to experiment with the symbols, carving them into stone and metal and imbuing them with different magical properties. Over time, they discovered that by combining different runes and binding them to anchors, they could create powerful spells that allowed them to do many things like teleporting, or creating powerful wards and enchantments. Yet another growth spurt in the development and history of the Dwarves.<br>
As their mastery of Runebinding grew, so too did their reputation as master craftsmen. They began to craft magical artifacts of immense power.<br>]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\dwarves.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Dwarves.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 13:23:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Grippli]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Grippli are a reclusive people that have inhabited the eastern swamps of <a data-href="Moordath" href="\Moordath" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moordath</a> since the <a data-href="Primordial Era" href="\timelines\primordial-era.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Primordial Era</a>.<br><br><br>Grippli resemble humanoid frogs, and exhibit a remarkable diversity in skin color, ranging from hues of blue and various shades of green to earthy browns and, in rare instances, vibrant oranges. This diversity serves a dual purpose in their swampy habitat. Those with skin colors closely resembling the swamp's natural tones are well-camouflaged, making them adept at stealth and hunting. Conversely, brighter and more vibrant skin tones often signal toxicity, serving as a warning to potential predators.<br>
A Grippli grows quickly, reaching adult size of about 2 feet in height about 3 years after hatching, though they're only considered adults around age 12. Grippli rarely live beyond 60 years, though exceptional individuals occasionally live as long as a century.<br><br>Gripplis lead a sophisticated hunter-gatherer lifestyle with which they reshape the landscape to suit their needs: building spillways to trap fish, seeding fruit-bearing trees, sowing cover-granting foliage for future hunts, and more techniques that often escape an agriculturist's eye. These strategies rely on community cooperation as well as dispersed populations, so gripplis commonly live in small villages, each part of a complex web of alliances and relationships. Reclusiveness has preserved grippli lives and lifestyles for millennia, yet they increasingly find themselves threatened by ancient evils and new explorers alike.<br><br>Central to Grippli belief systems is the veneration of the primal forces that sustain their swampy world. They hold deep reverence for "<a data-href="The Everflow" href="\The Everflow" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Everflow</a>," a spiritual embodiment of the ebb and flow of water throughout the marsh. This spirit represents not only life but also death, reflecting the cyclical nature of existence within their unique ecosystem.<br><br>Typical foods one would find with Grippli adventurer's are assortments of insects, sometimes grilled, sometimes raw. Over the centuries, Grippli cuisine has become more sophisticated, utilizing grasses like <a data-href="Sedgegrass" href="\flora\grasses\sedgegrass.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Sedgegrass</a>, as well as various mushrooms. The most notable and unique feature of Grippli cuisine is something that makes it very alien to other people: The <a data-href="Waterweaver" href="\fauna\insects\waterweaver.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Waterweaver</a>'s venom. Grippli are immune to it, and just like the spicy taste it gives off to them. To everyone else, ingesting enough of this food can paralyze them.<br><br>Grippli names often include resonant vowels and chirped consonants that remain difficult for non-gripplis to vocalize properly. Gripplis that travel widely often adopt one or more names more easily replicated by their associates.<br><br>Aalpo'ol, Bogwynne, Ctaprak, Eegru, Gpoun, Gruoksh, Hrrauti, Iopo, Iykiki, Kyrsiik, Mhruugu, Oplugo, Quaasol, Yolkuu, Ztaal<br><br>Mechanically, Grippli are similar to the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a>, with two additions: Poison Resistance and Aquatic Adaptation<br>
Hit points: 6<br>
Size: Small<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Dexterity, Wisdom, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Strength<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grippli  (Language)" data-href="Grippli  (Language)" href="\Grippli  (Language)" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Grippli</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, and you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br>Your affinity for the natural world grants you protection against some of its dangers. You gain poison resistance equal to half your level, and you gain a +1 status bonus to saving throws against poisons.<br><br>Your amphibian biology allows you to hold your breath for a long time. You gain the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Feats.aspx?ID=763" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Feats.aspx?ID=763" target="_blank">Breath Control</a>&nbsp;general feat as a bonus feat.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=46" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=46</a><br><br><br>In the Primordial Era, the Grippli emerged as one of the earliest sentient beings in Moordath. Their physical resemblance to humanoid frogs, combined with a diverse range of skin colors served them well in the swampy expanses of their homeland. This era laid the groundwork for their sophisticated hunter-gatherer lifestyle, which was intricately tied to the swamp's ecosystem. The Grippli harnessed the landscape to their advantage, building spillways for fishing and sowing vegetation that would later aid in hunting. This period marked the beginning of their deep-seated reverence for "The Everflow," a spiritual force embodying the water's cyclical journey through life and death. While the Grippli stayed as hunter-gatherers for the most part, <a data-href="Lizardfolk" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\lizardfolk.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Lizardfolk</a> developed a civilization. From this arose conflict, while Lizardfolk still live close and in harmony with nature by human standards, the Grippli are of a different opinion. <br><br>The Era of Storms tested the Grippli resilience like nothing before. The cataclysmic <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> reshaped the geography of Moordath, turning once-familiar territories into unrecognizable landscapes. Amidst this chaos, the Grippli adaptability and communal spirit shone brightly. Their dispersed villages, each a node in a complex web of alliances, became beacons of stability. The Grippli refined their techniques for living in harmony with the now volatile environment, further cementing their bond with The Everflow. This era also saw the Grippli defending their lands against new threats as ancient evils stirred and explorers encroached upon their territories. The Grippli mastery of stealth and their use of the environment as a defense mechanism ensured their survival through these dark times. <br><br>As the Era of Storms gave way to the Era of Legends, the Grippli faced the dawn of a new age with cautious optimism. Despite their reclusive nature, the challenges of this era pushed some Grippli beyond the boundaries of their swamps. They ventured into the wider world, carrying with them the knowledge of their people and a cuisine utterly alien to other races.<br>The Grippli involvement in the affairs of the Era of Legends was not without its conflicts. The attempted expansion of other civilizations into their territories tested their resolve. Yet, it was their unyielding spirit and deep-rooted connection to their homeland that saw them through. The Grippli mastery of the landscape, their sophisticated societal structures, and their devout worship of The Everflow enabled them to navigate these challenges. Reluctantly, they share Moordath with the <a data-href="Lizardfolk" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\lizardfolk.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Lizardfolk</a>, as they share the common goal of keeping their land safe.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\grippli.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Grippli.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 13:24:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lizardfolk]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Lizardfolk (sometimes referred to as Marshkin) are a sentient species native to the Swamps of Moordath, located in the far east of Kataris.<br><br><br>Lizardfolk manifest as imposing figures, bearing the hallmark traits of their reptilian lineage with distinct, adaptive features that vary with their environment. Standing between 6 to 7 feet tall on average, they continue to grow in strength and stature throughout their lives. Their scales, a natural armor, range in color from the muted grays, greens, and browns of the desert and temperate regions to the vibrant hues found in tropical locales, aiding in their camouflage. Dorsal spikes and striking neck frills, emblematic of their clan lineage, adorn their robust bodies, while toothy snouts and powerful tails underscore their predatory nature. Their equipment, crafted from materials like stone, ivory, glass, and bone, reflects a utilitarian ethos that prioritizes resilience in the face of moisture-rich environments.<br><br>Lizardfolk societies are deeply rooted in the principles of adaptation and resilience, mirroring the ecological diversity of their homeland. Their civilization, marked by a synthesis of complex social structures and a profound connection with nature, is one of the earliest scholars know of today. Villages and settlements are often led by a council of the wisest and most venerable members, who guide their people in matters of governance, warfare, and spirituality. Despite their formidable reputation as unflinching warriors and rangers, Lizardfolk place a strong emphasis on community, cooperation, and the stewardship of their natural resources, living in a delicate balance with the ecosystems that sustain them.<br><br>The spiritual life of the Lizardfolk is centered around the veneration of <a data-href="The Everflow" href="\The Everflow" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Everflow</a>, a transcendent force embodying the perpetual movement of water through their marshland realm. This belief system, shared with the Grippli, highlights a deep reverence for the cyclical nature of life, death, and rebirth, reflecting the eternal interplay of creation and destruction within their environment. Rituals and ceremonies often take place in sacred groves or along the banks of revered waterways, where the Lizardfolk commune with the primal energies that animate their world.<br><br>Lizardfolk culinary practices are a testament to their resourcefulness and deep understanding of their environment. Their diet primarily consists of fish, amphibians, and various aquatic and land-based flora. Utilizing stone ovens and smoking pits, they create dishes that are both nourishing and sustainable. Exotic spices and herbs, cultivated in the lush undergrowth of the swamps, add unique flavors to their cuisine, making it a rich and varied tapestry of tastes.<br><br>Once a year, in a traditional ceremony, Lizardfolk communities large enough engage in a sacred practice. The ritual involves the selection of the eldest among them, who is then ceremoniously outcast to the seas. This act is performed with the belief that the sacrifice of one of their most venerable members will appease the primal forces that surround and permeate Moordath, ensuring the protection and prosperity of their community for another year.<br>
The feast thrown in honor of the chosen elder is a vibrant affair, marked by an abundance of food, music, and storytelling. It's a time for the community to come together, celebrating the elder's achievements, wisdom, and the honor they bring to their kin by accepting this sacred duty. The atmosphere is one of joy and pride, with the elder at the heart of the festivities, surrounded by loved ones and community members expressing their respect and gratitude.<br><br>Lizardfolk names come from their ancient language and tend to be traditional. Names are typically chosen by the clan’s astrologer in accordance to omens and which star signs are ascendant when a Lizardfolk's egg hatches.<br><br>Arasheg, Barashk, Essaru, Enshuk, Gishkim, Hazi, Inishish, Kutak, Nasha, Shulkuru, Tizkar, Utakish, Zelkekek<br><br>Mechanically, Lizardfolk are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 8<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Strength, Wisdom, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Intelligence<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-href="Iruxi" href="\Iruxi" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Iruxi</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, and you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br>Your reptilian biology allows you to hold your breath for a long time. You gain the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Feats.aspx?ID=763" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Feats.aspx?ID=763" target="_blank">Breath Control</a>&nbsp;general feat as a bonus feat.<br><br>Your sharp claws offer an alternative to the fists other humanoids bring to a fight. You have a claw unarmed attack that deals 1d4 slashing damage and has the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=170" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=170" target="_blank">agile</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=179" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=179" target="_blank">finesse</a>&nbsp;traits.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=15" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=15</a><br><br><br>The Lizardfolk trace their origins back to the dawn of time, emerging as one of the first sentient beings to inhabit Caitha. This era saw them develop a deep bond with the natural world, laying the foundational elements of their society and belief systems.<br><br>Marked by tumultuous changes, violent <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> and external threats, the Lizardfolk honed their martial prowess and strategic acumen. It was during this period that they started steering further away from nature than the Grippli, leading to initial conflicts but eventually forging a reluctant alliance in the face of common enemies and the shared goal of protecting their homeland.<br><br>As new powers rose, the Lizardfolk, alongside the Grippli, stood firm as the protectors of Moordath. Their ancient civilization, while maintaining its deep-rooted traditions, began to evolve in response to the challenges and opportunities of this new era, embodying the resilience and adaptability that have always been their hallmarks.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\lizardfolk.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Lizardfolk.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 13:24:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Elves]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>As an ancient people, elves have seen great change and have the perspective that can come only from watching the arc of history. After the <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> that now encircle the world reached their lands, they were forced to migrate to the far west of <a data-href="Aroa" href="\geographic-elements\continents\aroa.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Aroa</a>, and even <a data-href="Antaris" href="\geographic-elements\continents\antaris.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Antaris</a>. They still struggle to reclaim their ancestral homes.<br>Elves combine otherworldly grace, sharp intellect, and mysterious charm in a way that is practically magnetic to members of other ancestries. <br>Elves are often rather private, steeped in the secrets of their people and kinship groups. They’re slow to build friendships outside their kinsfolk, but for a specific reason: they subtly and deeply attune to their environment and their companions.<br><br><br>Standing slightly taller than the average human, they possess lithe, slender frames that hint at both their grace and agility. Their skin tones range from the pale hues reflective of their northern origins to the rich, deep tones acquired from their southern migrations, mirroring the diverse environments they have traversed.<br>
Elves gradually adapt to their environment and their companions, and they often take on physical traits reflecting their surroundings. An elf who has dwelled in primeval forests for centuries, for example, might exhibit verdant hair and gnarled fingers, while one who’s lived in a desert might have golden pupils and skin. Elven fashion, like the elves themselves, tends to reflect their surroundings. Elves living in the forests and other wilderness locales wear clothing that plays off the terrain and flora of their homes, while those who live in cities tend to wear the latest fashions.  <br>Elves reach physical adulthood around the age of 20, though they aren’t considered to be fully emotionally mature by other elves until closer to the passing of their first century, once they’ve experienced more, held several occupations, and outlived a generation of shorter-lived people. A typical elf can live to around 600 years old.<br><br>Elves hold deeply seated ideals of individualism, allowing each elf to explore multiple occupations before alighting on a particular pursuit or passion that suits her best. Elves bear notorious grudges against rivals, which elves call ‘ilduliel,' but these antagonistic relationships can sometimes blossom into friendships over time. <br><br>Elvish religion centers around the worship of time and nature, which they perceive as intricately linked forces that shape the cosmos. They venerate the Veil of Aeons, a metaphysical concept representing the flow of time as a veil that separates different epochs but occasionally merges them during pivotal events. Elves believe in preserving the balance between the temporal and natural worlds, and their rituals often involve offerings to the Veil to ensure harmonious transitions and stability. Key deities in their pantheon include:<br>
<br>Aeluin, the Warden of Stars: Protector of cosmic order and the guide for elves on starlit paths.
<br>Talindë, the Whisper of the Winds: Embodiment of change and adaptability, revered during migrations and new beginnings.
<br><br>Elvish cuisine favours foraged ingredients, and their dishes are usually light but nourishing, designed to sustain them through their long lives and extensive travels.<br><br>An elf keeps their personal name secret among their family, while giving a nickname when meeting other people. This nickname can change over time, due to events in the elf's life or even on a whim. A single elf might be known by many names by associates of different ages and regions.<br>
Elven names consist of multiple syllables and are meant to flow lyrically—at least in the Elven tongue.<br><br>First Names<br><br>Mechanically, Elves are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 6<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 30ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Dexterity, Intelligence, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Constitution<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-href="Elven" href="\Elven" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Elven</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=60" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=60</a><br><br><br>The elves, during the Primordial Era, were deeply connected to the magical essence of Aroa. They developed a symbiotic relationship with the ancient forests, learning to harness and shape the natural magic around them. This period was marked by a flourishing of elven culture and the construction of their ethereal cities, which blended seamlessly into the natural landscapes.<br><br><a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>, massive tempests with arcane power, began to encircle the world, devastating the ancient forests and elven cities in their path. Faced with the destruction of their ancestral homes, the elves were forced to migrate westward.<br>The journey was perilous, marked by losses and sacrifices. However, it also led to a profound transformation in elven society. As they traveled, they spread their influence and adapted to new environments, from the dense, shadowy forests of western Aroa to the distant, mystical shores of Antaris.<br>In Antaris, the elves encountered new challenges and opportunities. They began to rebuild, using the lessons of the Highstorms to construct more resilient communities. This migration not only changed the geographical spread of the elves but also deepened their connection to the Veil of Aeons, reinforcing their beliefs in the cyclical nature of time and the importance of adaptation.<br>The Era of Storms is remembered as a time of great trial but also great evolution, as it was this period that truly defined the modern elven identity: a people shaped by their history, resilient and ever-adapting to the world's ever-changing nature.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\elves.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Elves.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 14:00:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gnomes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Always hungry for new experiences, gnomes constantly wander both mentally and physically, attempting to stave off a terrible ailment that threatens all of their people. This affliction, known as the Bleaching, strikes gnomes who fail to dream, innovate, and take in new experiences. The Bleaching slowly drains the color— literally—from gnomes, and it plunges those affected into states of deep depression that eventually claim their lives. Very few gnomes survive this scourge, becoming deeply morose and wise survivors known as bleachlings.<br><br>Most gnomes stand just over 3 feet in height and weigh little more than a human child. They exhibit a wide range of natural skin, hair, and eye colors. For gnomes that haven't begun the Bleaching, nearly any hair and eye color other than white is possible, with vibrant colors most frequent, while skin tones span a slightly narrower spectrum and tend toward earthy tones and pinkish hues, though occasionally green, black, or pale blue.  <br>Gnomes typically reach physical maturity at the age of 18, though many gnomes maintain a childlike curiosity about the world even into adulthood. A gnome can theoretically live to any age if they can stave off the Bleaching indefinitely, but in practice gnomes rarely live longer than around 400 years.<br><br>While most gnomes adopt some of the cultural practices of the region in which they live, they tend to pick and choose, adjusting their communities to fit their own logic. This often leads to majority gnome communities eventually consisting almost entirely of gnomes, as other people, bewildered by gnomish political decisions, choose to move elsewhere. Gnomes have little culture that they would consider entirely their own. Exceptionally few gnome kingdoms or nations exist in Caitha, with the only notable exception being <a data-href="Iwaî" href="\Iwaî" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Iwaî</a><br>By necessity, few gnomes marry for life, instead allowing relationships to run their course before amicably moving on, the better to stave off the Bleaching with new experiences. Though gnome families tend to be small, many gnome communities raise children communally, with fluid family boundaries. <br><br>Gnomes aren't a religious folk, though theological researchers and scholars do exist, researching all types of deities and trying to find out the substance of different religions.<br><br>Gnome cuisine is as inventive and diverse as the gnomes themselves, focusing heavily on the fusion of unusual flavours. Miniature dishes are popular, packed with intense flavours.<br><br>Gnome names can get quite complex and polysyllabic. Gnomes rarely concern themselves with how easy their names are to pronounce, and they often go by shorter nicknames. Among gnomes, the shorter the name, the more feminine it's considered to be.<br><br>Abroshtor, Bastargre, Besh, Fijit, Halungalom, Krolmnite, Neji, Majet, Pai, Poshment, Queck, Trig, Zarzuket, Zatqualmie<br><br>Mechanically, Gnomes are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 8<br>
Size: Small<br>
Speed: 25 feet<br>
Ability Boosts: Constitution, Charisma, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Strength<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-href="Gnomish" href="\Gnomish" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Gnomish</a>, as well as Fey, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=61" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=61</a><br><br>You can see in dim light as though it were bright light, so you ignore the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Conditions.aspx?ID=4" target="_blank">concealed</a>&nbsp;condition due to dim light.<br><br><br>In the Primordial Era, gnomes were widely regarded as the known world's first alchemists and scholars, inhabiting sprawling underground networks that spanned the depths of Sutaris. These ancient burrows below the <a data-href="Barawî Desert" href="\Barawî Desert" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Barawî Desert</a>, known as <a data-href="the Warrens" href="\the Warrens" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">the Warrens</a>, served as both homes and laboratories, places where gnomes could indulge their insatiable curiosity without the distractions of the surface world. During this period, gnomes perfected the art of elemental transmutation and pioneered early magical technologies, setting the stage for their future as innovators and creators.<br><br>As the Highstorms began to ravage the surface of Caitha, the gnomes retreated deeper into their Warrens, sealing themselves away from the chaos above. The storms' violent energies penetrated even these depths, however, forcing the gnomes to innovate rapidly to safeguard their sanctuaries. This era saw the development of energy dampening fields and reinforced magical wards, technologies that would later become central to gnomish culture.<br>Isolated from the surface for centuries, gnome society became even more eccentric and insular. The constant need for new experiences to combat the Bleaching turned their underground dwellings into bizarre landscapes of magical invention and whimsical architecture. Community bonds strengthened as they relied on each other not just for survival but for the new ideas essential to stave off their affliction.<br>During this time, legends of bleachlings—those rare gnomes who survived the Bleaching—began to emerge. These bleachlings, with their morose wisdom and faded hues, became revered as oracles and advisors, their insights shaped by centuries of accumulated experiences.<br><br>When the storms were finally magically banished to the edges of the known world, the gnomes emerged from their subterranean retreats to find a dramatically altered landscape. The desert of Barawî, once a fringe wasteland, had become a much less hostile place to live, and attracted settlers from other parts of the world. A river broke free from the mountains in the east and carved its way to the ocean, leaving a much more fertile land behind.<br>It was here that the gnomes reclaimed Iwaî, a city-state that again quickly became a hub of technological innovation and gnomish sciences. Freed from the confines of their underground realms, gnomes embraced the open skies and vast horizons, channeling their inherent curiosity into projects that transformed Iwaî into a wonder of the modern world.<br>The architecture of Iwaî reflected both the whimsy and the ingenuity of its inhabitants—buildings with self-adjusting foundations and walls that changed color with the temperature, all powered by sustainable magical sources. The city became a magnet for scholars, inventors, and adventurers from across the world, drawn by its reputation as a center of progress and a beacon of new beginnings.<br>Gnomes, now mingling more with other races, began to influence the broader cultural landscape of Caitha. While still retaining their quirky, insular tendencies within their city-state, they became known as diplomats and traders, eager to share their discoveries and learn from the outside world to keep the Bleaching at bay.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\gnomes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Gnomes.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 14:41:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Goblins]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br><br>Goblins are a vibrant and tenacious species, known for their distinctive appearance that makes them stand out in any crowd. They typically stand about 3 feet tall and possess a peculiar, if not endearing, physique: large, bulbous heads balanced on scrawny limbs, their skin a kaleidoscope of greens, grays, and blues. Their large, bat-like ears and sharp, beady red eyes give them a mischievous look, as though they’re always plotting their next prank or adventure. Despite their small size, goblins are resilient, their bodies adapted to the harsh conditions of their mountainous desert home.<br><br>Goblins bond closely with their allies, fiercely protecting those companions who have protected them or offered a sympathetic ear. Goblins tend to assume for their own protection that members of taller ancestries, which goblins often refer to colloquially as “longshanks,” won't treat them kindly. Learning to trust longshanks is difficult for a goblin, and it's been only in recent years that such a partnership has even been an option. <br><br>Goblins in Caitha don’t follow a formal religion; instead, they practice a sort of animism, seeing the spirit and value in everything around them. They have a particular reverence for fire, which they consider a living entity that speaks only to them. This "<a data-href="Flame Tongue" href="\Flame Tongue" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Flame Tongue</a>" belief is central to many of their cultural practices, from cooking to storytelling, where the fire’s crackle dictates the rhythm of their tales.<br><br>Goblin cuisine is as wild and unpredictable as the goblins themselves. They are culinary adventurers, often creating dishes from whatever they can scavenge, which surprisingly results in meals that are as explosive in flavor as they are in nature. A typical goblin feast might include:<br>
Anything skewerable, roasted over an open flame until it pops, and spicy, fermented cactus fruit, mashed and mixed with crispy insects.<br><br>Even the most well-intentioned goblins have trouble following the rules, meaning goblin adventurers are often unsure whether they're on the right side of the law. <br><br>Goblin names tend to be guttural and quirky, often reflecting their impulsive nature. Names are given based on a notable event at birth or an early childhood trait, and they stick for life, no matter how odd.<br><br>
<br>Gritjaw
<br>Sneakwhistle
<br>Blazebug
<br><br>Mechanically, Goblins are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 6<br>
Size: Small<br>
Speed: 25 feet<br>
Ability Boosts: Dexterity, Charisma, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Wisdom<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and <a data-href="Goblin (Language)" href="\Goblin (Language)" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Goblin (Language)</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=62" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=62</a><br><br><br>In the earliest days, goblins were nomadic scavengers in the red desert mountains of Caitha. Their society was loosely organized, with family clans moving where survival was easiest. During this era, they developed a knack for storytelling, using tales to pass on survival tactics and to entertain during the long desert nights.<br><br>As the Highstorms began to ravage Caitha, the goblins’ survival instincts kicked into high gear. They pooled their collective cunning to construct Riqitt, a fortress that served as a safe haven from the storms' fury. Nestled in the mountain crags, Riqitt was built from scavenged materials and reinforced with whatever the goblins could craft.<br>This era marked a significant shift in goblin society from nomadic bands to a more settled community, though their love for chaos and mischief never waned. The storms themselves became central in goblin tales, depicted as battles with sky giants they tricked and defeated.<br><br>With the Highstorms pushed to the boundaries of the known world, the goblins of Riqitt began to venture out once more. Their capital emptied as more and more goblins left. While it isn't completely empty, it is not as populated as you might expect from seeing the city from afar.<br>The modern goblin community thrives on its eccentricities and innovations. While they still cherish their independence and chaotic lifestyle, they've become integral to the cultural and economic tapestry of Caitha. Goblins are now as likely to be found trading in markets as anywhere, always with a story to tell and a spark in their eyes.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\goblins.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Goblins.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 14:40:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Humans]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Humans are diverse and adaptable people with wide potential and deep ambitions.<br><br><br>Humans' physical characteristics are as varied as the world's climes. Humans have a wide variety of skin and hair colors, body types, and facial features. Generally speaking, their skin has a darker hue the closer to the equator they or their ancestors lived.<br>
A typical human can live to be around 90 years old. Humans have exceptionally mutable physical characteristics compared to other ancestries, with greater variance in height, weight, and other physical parameters.<br><br>Human variety also manifests in terms of their governments, attitudes, and social norms. Though the oldest of human cultures can trace their shared histories thousands of years into the past, when compared to the societies of the elves or dwarves, human civilizations seem in a state of constant flux as empires fragment and new kingdoms subsume the old.<br><br>Mechanically, Humans are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 8<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 25 feet<br>
Ability Boosts: Two free ability boosts<br>
Ability Flaws: None<br><br>You can speak, read, and write Common and additional languages equal to 1 + your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=64" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=64</a><br><br><br>Humans in Caitha developed very similarly to the <a data-href="Kanee" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanee</a> or <a data-href="Mossin (Halflings)" href="\player-character-options\ancestries\mossin-(halflings).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Mossin (Halflings)</a>, with small tribes of hunter-gatherers moving through the landscape and relying on natural resources around them for survival. These early humans were nomadic, moving with the seasons to follow game animals and to take advantage of seasonal food sources such as berries, nuts and roots.<br>
Over time, as humans began to develop agriculture and settle in more permanent communities, their culture became more complex. In the Mediterranean climate of Caitha, early human settlements were focused around the cultivation of olives, grapes and wheat, which allowed for the development of trade networks and the establishment of larger, more organized communities.<br>As these settlements grew, they began to develop their own unique cultures and social structures. Some became more egalitarian, with power shared among the members of the community, while others developed hierarchical systems with chiefs or kings at the top. Religion also played a significant role in many early human societies, with <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Gods" data-href="Gods" href="\Gods" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">deities</a> worshipped for their ability to bring fertility to the land, protect the community from harm or guide human actions.<br><br>As the human-caused <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> swept across Caitha, civilizations faced unprecedented trials. This era, characterized by its relentless, catastrophic weather, brought about a significant reshaping of human societies. Cities crumbled, coastlines changed, and entire regions were rendered unrecognizable, forcing humans to either flee to safer grounds or innovate ways to survive.<br>Human adaptability was crucial during these times. They built fortified settlements, adapted agriculture to volatile climates, and formed new alliances, sometimes with other species, to enhance their chances of survival. The storms, while destructive, also served as a catalyst for technological and magical advancements. Humans, often at the forefront of innovation, pioneered developments in storm prediction and weatherproof architecture.<br>Communities that once might have warred with each other found common ground, united by the need to survive. New leaderships emerged, often marked by a more collective, survival-focused mentality rather than the traditional hierarchies of the past.<br><br>With the eventual abatement of the Highstorms, confined now to the outer edges of the known world, humans entered what would be known as the Era of Legends—a time of rebuilding and exploration, but also a time of new imperialist wars. Freed from the constant threat of stormy destruction, human societies flourished and expanded, both in population and cultural influence.<br>The new era brought about a renaissance of arts, culture, and science as humans explored not only their changed world but also the realms of magic and technology made possible through their innovations during the storms. Cities were rebuilt with grander visions, incorporating both the aesthetic and practical technologies developed during the darker times.<br>Human explorers set out to rediscover lost lands, establish new trade routes, and exchange knowledge with other species whose capabilities and technologies had also been shaped by the storms. Diplomacy flourished as humans sought to solidify their place in a world that was increasingly interconnected.<br>Meanwhile, scholars and mystics delved deeper into the understanding of magic, particularly that which had been influenced by the storms' arcane energies. This pursuit of knowledge led to a cultural golden age, where human universities and libraries became the centres of learning for all races of Caitha.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\humans.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Humans.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 14:53:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Kanee]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The Kanee or Kanei (sometimes referred to as Night-Elves or Dark-Elves, even though they are not related to elves) are a race inhabiting parts of the northern tundras of <a data-href="Kataris" href="\geographic-elements\continents\kataris.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kataris</a>.<br>
They emerged as a sapient species from the <a data-href="Kanrak" href="\fauna\mammals\kanrak.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanrak</a>, who had adapted to survive the harsh and icy environment of the northern tundras. <br><br><br>Kanee are a stout and resilient race, evolved from the rugged Kanrak of the harsh tundra. Standing shorter than the average human but with broad, muscular frames, Kanee possess remarkable strength and endurance. Their most distinctive features are their large, curved horns, which serve not only as symbols of their heritage but also as canvases for their cultural expressions. The Kanee’s eyes are another unique trait; capable of turning entirely black, these eyes enhance their night vision, a mysterious adaptation from their evolutionary predecessors. Their skin tones range from deep dark blue to lighter shades, often accented by the vibrant, painted horns that tell stories of lineage and personal achievement.<br><br><br>The predominant religion among the Kanee is the worship of <a data-href="Roor" href="\Roor" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Roor</a>, the deity symbolizing fire, life, warmth, and light. Known as the Followers of the Flame, this faith centers around Roor, who is revered not only as a creator and sustainer but also as a destroyer who can wield fire to protect and to punish. Roor is depicted as a towering figure enveloped in flames, representing the eternal and life-giving warmth that sustains the Kanee through the harsh tundra winters.<br><br>Kanee cuisine reflects their tundran herbivore origins, and is not particularly exciting compared to other cuisines of the world. It consists of stew and bread, berries, mushrooms and lichen, and they can digest many different plants. <br><br><br>Horn painting is a long standing tradition in Kanee culture, daring back to the earliest days of their sapience. The Kanee believe that their horns, which are a prominent feature of their physiology, are a symbol of their ancestral roots and connection to their land. Painting their horns is a way for them to express this connection and celebrate their heritage.<br>
The process of horn-painting involves using natural dyes made from crushed berries, lichens and other plant materials to create intricate designs on the horns. The designs often include abstract images of animals, landscapes, and other symbols meaningful to the Kanee.<br>
Horn-painting is typically done during important cultural events, such as the coming-of-age ceremony for young Kanee. The designs are meant to be a reflection of the individual, as well as their connection to their community and the natural world. Over time, this practive has evolved into a complex art form, with skilled artisans creating intricate and detailed designs that are admired and sought after by everyone. It has become an important part of Kanee culture, helping to preserve their traditions and connect them to their past.<br><br>Ancestral worship is an important aspect of Kanee culture, and is deeply intertwined with their reverence for the natural world. The Kanee believe that the spirits of their ancestors continue to exist in the world, and can offer guidance. To honor and maintain a connection with their ancestors, the Kanee often keep the horns of their dead and make them into ceremonial horns.<br>
The horns are believed to contain the essence of the ancestor's soul, and by blowing into the horn, the living Kanee can communicate with and pay respects to their departed loved ones. This practice is particularly important during ceremonies and rituals, such as births, coming of age and funerals.<br>
The ancient practive of hornpainting reinforced this type of worship, as it better preserves the memory of the deceased and acknowledges the impact they had on the world during their lifetime. <br><br>Kanee Surnames often reflect the natural world and their personal or family achievements, incorporating elements that signify strength, endurance, or a connection to their environment.<br><br>Surnames<br>
Strongshield, Wintermane, Icecaller, Frostwalker, Snowbinder<br><br>Kanee do not exist on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 8<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 25 feet<br>
Ability Boosts: Strength, Constitution, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Dexterity<br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br>Due to your species' evolutionary history, you cannot digest meat of any type. Your diet consists of plants and mushrooms, which your body turns into energy a lot more efficiently than that of a Human or Dwarf.<br><br>You speak, read and write Common and <a data-href="Kanar" href="\languages\kanar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Kanar</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>I have not currently written up any custom heritages for this. Please use the following trait, shamelessly stolen from othe Wintertouched Human heritage:<br>You gain&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=27" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Traits.aspx?ID=27" target="_blank">cold</a>&nbsp;resistance equal to half your level (minimum 1), and you treat&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Rules.aspx?ID=642" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Rules.aspx?ID=642" target="_blank">environmental cold effects</a>&nbsp;as if they were one step less extreme (incredible cold becomes extreme, extreme cold becomes severe, and so on).<br><br><br>Early Kanee culture was based on nomadic tribes that followed herds of migratory animals for food and resources. Scholars are not sure how they discovered fire in the tundra, but it was likely by accident, through a natural wildfire caused by powerful lighting strikes. They quickly learned how to control and use fire for warmth, cooking and protection against predators. Fire was seen as a valuable resource and played a significant role in early Kanee culture, with many myths and legends featuring it prominently.<br>
As Kanee society developed and expanded, they began to settle in permanent locations and developed agriculture and animal husbandry. This allowed for larger populations to thrive, and more complex societies to emerge.<br>
As the Kanee became more advanced, they began to keep written records of their history, culture, and achievements. The first writings emerged around 2000 years ago, and marked the beginning of a new era of Kanee civilization. <br><br>These early writings documented the rise and fall of the first Kanee kingdoms around <a data-href="Khalan" href="\Khalan" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Khalan</a>, <a data-href="Joskja" href="\Joskja" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Joskja</a> and <a data-href="Ivarja" href="\Ivarja" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ivarja</a>, while the <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a> were ravaging the world, which were characterized by central governments, organized military and elaborate public works. A time of expansion began for the Kanee, as they discovered seafaring and were the first to arrive to the <a data-href="island chain in the northwest of Kataris" href="\island chain in the northwest of Kataris" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">island chain in the northwest of Kataris</a> and at the north pole of Caitha. Having a natural physiological advantage over other races in the cold, they had almost no competition with settling and expanding there.<br><br>Following the tumultuous Era of Storms, the Kanee found themselves in a world reshaped by elemental forces. With the stabilization of the Highstorms at the world’s edge, the Kanee entered the Era of Legends, a time when they could finally turn from mere survival to the restoration and advancement of their culture.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\kanee.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Kanee.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 11:25:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mossin (Halflings)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br><br>Mossin, often referred to as Halflings, are a small humanoid race known for their resilience and resourcefulness. Standing no taller than the average human child, they are roughly 90 cm in height and weigh between 30 to 60 kg. Their builds are stocky, and their long arms are well-suited to their burrowing lifestyle. Mossin skin colors vary widely, complementing the diverse environment of the savanna. Their large, expressive eyes are typically yellow or orange, though green and blue are rare but cherished. Mossin pride themselves on their variety of braided hairstyles, which range in color from black to brown to grey. <br><br><br>The Mossin practice Suahin, an animistic faith deeply rooted in their connection to the natural world. They believe every element of nature—a rock, a river, a tree—possesses a spirit, or "Sua," which must be revered and respected. This spiritual outlook emphasizes harmony with the environment and guides their daily actions and decisions.<br><br>Mossin cuisine is a celebration of their agricultural and foraging skills, characterized by dishes that are both nutritious and flavorful. <br><br>Mossin villages, referred to as a burrow, consist of large communal areas with homes around it, organised in a circular pattern. They are typically located in the Savanna, where they live in harmony with the local flora and fauna. During the dry season, the burrows keep them safe from wildfires naturally, and during the wet season a combination of the large, round roof that is constructed over the burrows and elaborate channels protect them from floods. <br><br>Mossin names typically reflect aspects of nature or personal traits, and they often carry significant meaning within their communities.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://www.fantasynamegenerators.com/hobbit-names.php" target="_blank">https://www.fantasynamegenerators.com/hobbit-names.php</a><br><br>Mechanically, Halflings are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Ancestries.aspx?ID=59" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>
Hit points: 6<br>
Size: Small<br>
Speed: 25 ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Dexterity, Wisdom, Free<br>
Ability Flaws: Strength<br><br>You speak, read and write Common and <a data-href="Halfing (language)" href="\Halfing (language)" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Halfing (language)</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br>Your eyes are sharp, allowing you to make out small details about concealed or even invisible creatures that others might miss. You gain a +2 circumstance bonus when using the seek action to find hidden or undetected creatures within 30 feet of you. When you target an opponent that is concealed from you or hidden from you, reduce the DC of the flat check to 3 for a concealed target or 9 for a hidden one.<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=63" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=63</a><br><br><br>In their early prehistoric culture, the Mossin lived in small, nomadic tribes that roamed the vast Savannahs in search of food, and made homes for themselves by burrowing in the earth. These served as checkpoints along their migratory paths. They hunted and gathered using basic tools made from bone, stone and wood, and developed a deep knowledge of the flora and fauna of their environment. They also developed a rich spiritual culture, with a deep reverence for the natural world and the spirits that they believed inhabited it.<br>
Over time, the Mossin began to develop more complex social structures and systems of governance, as well as more advanced technologies and methods of substinence. They began to develop basic agricultural practives, domesticating certain plant and animal species to ensure a more stable food supply. They also becan to settle in more permanent structures they called Burrows, mostly circular villages and towns with large communal areas, with protection both from flooding and the wildifres that are common in the Savannah.<br>
Near the end of prehistory, three large Settlements were founded.<br>
As the Mossin developed more complex societies and ways of life, they began to develop a system of record-keeping to help them manage their increasingly complex communities. At first, this took the form of simple pictograms and symbols, which were etched into clay for less permanent, and bone for more permanent and important events or transactions. Over time, these symbols evolved into more complex systems of writing, allowing the Mossin to record and preserve their history and culture in ever-greater detail.<br>
The emergence of writing was a critical turning point in the history of the Mossin, allowing them to develop more sophisticated political systems and economic networks. It also allowed them to develop more advanced sciences and technologies, as well as a rich and diverse cultural heritage. In the centuries that followed, the Mossin continued to develop and refine their systems of writing and record-keeping, paving the way for the great empires and civilizations that would come to dominate their world in the years to come. <br><br>At the beginning of the Era of Storms, Mossin population in the Savannas was very large, and they expanded to other regions as well, but during the era of storms their population dwindeled dramatically, with many burrows being flooded, out-of-season wildfires spreading and killing crops and livestock and the resulting hunger. The Era of Storms left many fleeing the Savannas, and many burrows lost to time, abandoned, flooded and caved in.<br><br>Following the devastating Era of Storms, which saw many Mossin burrows lost to floods and wildfires, the Mossin population began a slow but determined resurgence. The savannas of Kataris, though scarred by natural calamities, remained their ancestral home. The Mossin rebuilt their burrows with improved designs—larger communal areas and more intricate flood and fire defenses, allowing them to withstand the extreme weather conditions more effectively.<br>
This time marked a significant evolution in Mossin governance. The largest settlements, Samaq and Qindra, united under a joint democratic government, founding the nation of Samaqindra. This alliance marked the birth of the first democracy in the known world, setting a precedent for future political structures and emphasizing the Mossin values of community and collective decision-making.<br>
As the Mossin expanded their trade networks, they interacted more frequently with neighboring human settlements and distant lands, such as the Dwarven city-states of the Iron Chain and the far northern Kanee Kingdoms. These interactions brought new goods and ideas, enriching Mossin culture and economy. The Mossin became renowned for their intricate handicrafts and their agricultural produce, particularly their herbal concoctions and hearty grains.<br>
Halflings today are known throughout the world. Claiming no place as their own outside of Samaqindra and Thejindra, halflings don't usually control settlements and live among humans within towns or larger cities, or, rarely, as hermits. ]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\mossin-(halflings).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Mossin (Halflings).md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2024 11:46:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Orcs]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
"In the shadow of storms and legends, the Orcs of Caitha stand tall, their spirits tempered by the trials of the past and their hearts guided by the virtues of honor and resilience."

<br>from "A Traveler's Guide to Brurogh", by Casper Mossbane

<br><br><br>Orcs are imposing figures, with muscular builds that speak to their warrior heritage. They typically stand over six feet tall, with green to gray skin that can sometimes carry a bluish hue. Their tusks, emerging from the lower jaw, are a mark of their race, varying in size but always present as a symbol of their strength and ferocity. Their eyes, often gold or red, shine with a depth of wisdom and the fire of their indomitable spirit. They have rough, leathery skin, thick bones and rock hard muscles, making them suited for physically demanding tasks.<br><br>Orcs living in areas with many other races are often perceived as somewhat rude or "standoffish," if not hostile, because they neither ask for help nor offer help, even in times of crisis, and are offended if someone tries to help unsolicited. There are rumors that they steal children, because if an Orc finds a child lost in the forest, they will feed it and - if they cannot find the parents or home - raise and integrate it.<br><br>Central to Orcish society is their spirituality, revolving around the worship of <a data-href="Garrosh" href="\religions\deities\garrosh.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Garrosh</a>, a deity of justice and honor. This spirituality guides their daily lives, emphasizing personal growth through adversity and the importance of community responsibility, especially towards children.<br>
Orcish spirituality states that a soul can only grow and become stronger by overcoming the challenges life presents to them. The challenge of supporting or interfering with someone else unsolicited is not only impolite but very hurtful - because you are taking away their chance to grow. Asking for help is something very personal, and doing so could be a way for an Orc to bond or be "too personal/intimate," depending on the existing relationship with the person. Children are an exception - for Orcs, all children are fundamentally the responsibility of the society/community, no matter whose child it is or whether the child is an Orc at all.<br><br>Orcish cuisine is hearty, reflecting their hunting and gathering heritage. Dishes often feature game, roots, and wild vegetables, seasoned with the herbs of the Katarisian forests. A common meal might include roasted boar, forest mushrooms, and a brew made from fermented berries.<br><br>Orcish names sound powerful and imposing, and are usually bestowed upon them in a ceremony by their parents or caretakers. They don't usually carry last names.<br><br>Garthok, Ertok, Nartha, Gnarg, Yargol, Nakgu, Durbul, Garothmuk<br><br>Mechanically, Orcs are the same as on <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://2e.aonprd.com/(X(1)S(uircgsflygijk355ocfo0cac))/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=66&amp;Redirected=1" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/(X(1)S(uircgsflygijk355ocfo0cac))/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=66&amp;Redirected=1" target="_blank">aonprd</a><br>Hit points: 10<br>
Size: Medium<br>
Speed: 25ft<br>
Ability Boosts: Strength, Free<br>
Ability Flaws:  -<br><br>Common, <a data-href="Orcish" href="\Orcish" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Orcish</a>, and additional languages equal to your INT modifier (if positive).<br><br><a rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=19" target="_blank">https://2e.aonprd.com/Heritages.aspx?Ancestry=19</a><br><br>You can see in darkness and dim light just as well as you can see in bright light, though your vision in darkness is in black and white.<br><br><br>The early history of the Orcs is marked by their struggle for survival in a stone-age world. They lived in close-knit nomadic tribes, relying on their strength and cunning to hunt and the wisdom of their elders to navigate the challenges of their environment. <br><br>This period brought catastrophic magical storms that ravaged Caitha, reshaping the land and testing the Orcs like never before. Their resilience during these times was unmatched, as they adapted to the chaos, protecting their communities and growing strong resentments towards the magic that flowed through their world in turmoil. Many tribes started to settle for more permanent homes for better protection.<br><br>After the storms were banished, the Orcs entered a period of rebuilding and growth. It was a time of heroes and legends, where the greatest tales of Orcish valor and wisdom were forged. Societies became more structured and the Orcs' deep respect for the natural world led them to form alliances with other races, sharing their knowledge of survival and spirituality.]]></description><link>player-character-options\ancestries\orcs.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Player Character Options/Ancestries/Orcs.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 07:23:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Highstorms]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="highstorms.png.webp" src="\lib\media\highstorms.png.webp"><br><br>Highstorms are a catastrophic natural phenomenon, characterized by their devastating impact on both the physical and metaphysical realms. Unlike conventional storms, Highstorms manifest with disconcerting moments of darkness instead of lightning flashes and emit high-pitched, eerie sounds rather than deep, rolling thunder. <br><br>Highstorms originated from the extensive and unrestrained use of weather manipulation magic by mages in a period predating the <a data-href="Era of Legends" href="\timelines\era-of-legends.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Legends</a> and the adoption of the Druidic Calendar. This form of magic, wielded to shape the world's climate, led to awe-inspiring changes but also had dangerous, unforeseen consequences. The Highstorms were an unintended side effect of this manipulation, disrupting the natural order and posing a severe threat to all known life.<br><br>
<br>Dark Flashes: Instead of traditional lightning, Highstorms produce moments of darkness that tear through the atmosphere.
<br>Eerie Sounds: The storms are accompanied by high-pitched, unsettling screeches, replacing the typical sound of thunder.
<br>Destructive Force: Highstorms possess the power to disrupt both the physical world and the fabric of reality itself, making them a dire threat to the known world.
<br><br>The emergence of Highstorms led to a schism among magic users. While many mages continued their pursuits, oblivious or indifferent to the consequences, a faction known as the Druids recognized the gravity of the situation. This division culminated in brutal magical wars, with casualties too numerous to count. Ultimately, the Druids emerged victorious, determined to rectify the mistakes of the past and banish the Highstorms.<br><br><a data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Druidic Sacrifice</a> marks the most pivotal and solemn event in the annals of the known world, signaling the end of the Era of Storms. Faced with the catastrophic impact of the Highstorms, the Druid Circles united in a secretive, large-scale ritual aimed at banishing the storms beyond the borders of the known world. This effort, however, came at an extraordinary cost: every Druid involved sacrificed their life, marking the ritual with a profound loss.<br>
The Druidic Sacrifice is commemorated as the official beginning of the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Time and the Calendar" data-href="Time and the Calendar" href="\timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a> and is a crucial part of Druidic heritage. It serves as a solemn reminder of the dangers of unchecked magical manipulation and the importance of preserving the natural order. Today, the manipulation of weather is outlawed across the world, sometimes even under penalty of death, as societies seek to prevent the recurrence of such cataclysms.<br><br>The nature of Highstorms and how they came about, led some people to believe there to be a higher power responsible for them, one who did not like how much magic users meddled with their affairs. They founded the <a data-href="Order of the Storms" href="\Order of the Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Order of the Storms</a>, a dark cult that tries to get rid of all magic users.<br><br>What lies beyond the Highstorms remains one of the greatest mysteries of the known world. The storms serve as a barrier, encapsulating the known world and keeping its inhabitants from discovering what lies beyond. Despite this, the Druids and other custodians of the world's natural order continue their vigil, ensuring that the Highstorms remain at bay and that the balance of the world is maintained.]]></description><link>fantastical-elements\highstorms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Fantastical Elements/Highstorms.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 07:17:24 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\highstorms.png.webp" length="0" type="image/webp"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\highstorms.png.webp"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Caitha]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="logo.png" src="\_attachments\logo.png" style="width: 650px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><br>Welcome to Caitha, dear reader.<br>
This worldbuilding project has been and still is a great journey that began in 2018, but has its roots in my childhood fascination with worldbuilding.<br>
I can trace this fascination back to about the age of 7, where my early attempts at map-making gave birth to many Island Nations, each proudly bearing the name "Joshuania".<br>
These miniature realms, with their train stations, sun-kissed beaches and grocery stores were my 7-year-old-self's vision of the perfect country, led, of course, by none other than me.<br>Now, with Caitha, my ambition has evolved. My goal is to breathe life into the fantasy world that has been brewing in my notes over the years, a world teaming with magic, history, and untold adventures. Caitha isn't just a static creation; it's a canvas for stories I might tell, a potential stage for epic quests in games like DnD or Pathfinder, or a backdrop for stories in whatever types of mediums I want to explore.<br>But even if I never venture beyond chronicling the history or writing about flora and fauna of Caitha, that's perfectly fine. The real joy for me at the moment lies in the act of building, in creating, in getting lost in the tapestry of this world, which is, in my mind, a lot more than I am currently capable of writing down.<br>So, whether you're here to explore or because I sent you the link eager to get some feedback on if the site is finally working or not:<br>
Welcome to Caitha.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Table of Elements" data-href="Table of Elements" href="\table-of-elements.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Enter</a><br><br><a data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Druidic Sacrifice</a>, a tale of sacrifice and the beginning of timekeeping.]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:09:37 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="_attachments\logo.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="_attachments\logo.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Table of Elements]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="logo.png" src="\_attachments\logo.png" style="width: 650px; max-width: 100%;"><br>the following list is structured after the "worldbuilding Table of Elements" by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.reddit.com/r/worldbuilding/comments/u55hfb/worldbuilding_table_of_elements/" rel="noopener" class="external-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/worldbuilding/comments/u55hfb/worldbuilding_table_of_elements/" target="_blank">u/otherAtlas</a><br>
traveler, beware! many articles listed here are not published yet and are still being refined<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Maps" href="\maps\maps.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Maps</a>
<br><a data-href="Timelines" href="\timelines\timelines.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Timelines</a> *
<br><a data-href="Time and the Calendar" href="\timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Time and the Calendar</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Ancestries" href="\player-character-options\ancestries.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ancestries</a> *
<br><a data-href="Heritages" href="\Heritages" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Heritages</a> *
<br><a data-href="Backgrounds" href="\Backgrounds" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Backgrounds</a>*
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Continents" href="\geographic-elements\continents.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Continents</a>
<br><a data-href="Seas and Oceans" href="\Seas and Oceans" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Seas and Oceans</a> *
<br><a data-href="Rivers and Lakes" href="\Rivers and Lakes" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Rivers and Lakes</a> *
<br><a data-href="States and Nations" href="\States and Nations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">States and Nations</a> *
<br><a data-href="Cities" href="\Cities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Towns" href="\Towns" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Towns</a> *
<br><a data-href="Villages &amp; Smaller" href="\Villages &amp; Smaller" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Villages &amp; Smaller</a> *
<br><br>Caitha has a temperate climate, with temperatures ranging from -50 degrees Celsius up to 40 degrees Celsius. The Surface of Caitha is mostly covered in oceans.<br>
<br><a data-href="Flora" href="\flora\flora.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Flora</a> *
<br><a data-href="Fauna" href="\fauna\fauna.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fauna</a> *
<br><a data-href="Ecosystems" href="\ecosystems\ecosystems.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ecosystems</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Architecture" href="\Architecture" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Architecture</a> *
<br><a data-href="Art" href="\Art" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Art</a> *
<br><a data-href="Fashion" href="\Fashion" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Fashion</a> *
<br><a data-href="Cuisine" href="\Cuisine" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cuisine</a> *
<br><a data-href="Etiquette and Taboos" href="\Etiquette and Taboos" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Etiquette and Taboos</a> *
<br><a data-href="Entertainment" href="\Entertainment" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Entertainment</a> *
<br><a data-href="Body Adornment" href="\Body Adornment" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Body Adornment</a>s *
<br><a data-href="Rituals" href="\Rituals" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Rituals</a> *
<br><a data-href="Celebrations" href="\Celebrations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Celebrations</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Guilds and other Organizations" href="\guilds\guilds-and-other-organizations.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Guilds and other Organizations</a>
<br><a data-href="Hierarchies" href="\Hierarchies" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Hierarchies</a> *
<br><a data-href="Heraldry and Vexillology" href="\Heraldry and Vexillology" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Heraldry and Vexillology</a> *
<br><a data-href="Calendars" href="\Calendars" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Calendars</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Recorded Histories" href="\Recorded Histories" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Recorded Histories</a> *
<br><a data-href="Legends and Tales" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Legends and Tales</a>
<br><a data-href="Artifacts" href="\Artifacts" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Artifacts</a> *
<br><a data-href="Ruins" href="\Ruins" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ruins</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Alphabets and Languages" href="\Alphabets and Languages" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Alphabets and Languages</a> *
<br><a data-href="Figures of Speech" href="\Figures of Speech" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Figures of Speech</a> *
<br><a data-href="Slangs and Curses" href="\Slangs and Curses" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Slangs and Curses</a> *
<br><a data-href="Lies and Propaganda" href="\Lies and Propaganda" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Lies and Propaganda</a> *
<br><a data-href="Long Distance Communication" href="\Long Distance Communication" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Long Distance Communication</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Tools" href="\Tools" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Tools</a> *
<br><a data-href="Arms and Armour" href="\Arms and Armour" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Arms and Armour</a> *
<br><a data-href="Medicine" href="\Medicine" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Medicine</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Governments" href="\Governments" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Governments</a> *
<br><a data-href="Diplomacy and Politics" href="\Diplomacy and Politics" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Diplomacy and Politics</a> *
<br><a data-href="Political Events" href="\Political Events" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Political Events</a> *
<br><a data-href="War" href="\War" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">War</a> *
<br><a data-href="Law and Order" href="\Law and Order" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Law and Order</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Currencies and Trade" href="\economics\currencies-and-trade.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Currencies and Trade</a> *
<br><a data-href="Businesses and Corporations" href="\Businesses and Corporations" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Businesses and Corporations</a> *
<br><a data-href="Rare Goods" href="\Rare Goods" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Rare Goods</a> *
<br><a data-href="Resources" href="\Resources" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Resources</a> *
<br><a data-href="Important Trade Routes" href="\Important Trade Routes" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Important Trade Routes</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Deities" href="\Deities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Deities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Religions" href="\Religions" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Religions</a> *
<br><a data-href="Sacred Texts" href="\Sacred Texts" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Sacred Texts</a> *
<br><a data-href="Afterlife Beliefs" href="\Afterlife Beliefs" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Afterlife Beliefs</a> *
<br><a data-href="Prophecies" href="\Prophecies" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Prophecies</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Magic/Magic in Caitha" href="\magic\magic-in-caitha.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magic/Magic in Caitha</a> *

<br><a data-href="Magic Language" href="\languages\magic-language.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magic Language</a> *
<br><a data-href="Druidic Magic" href="\Druidic Magic" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Magic</a> *
<br><a data-href="Magical Creatures" href="\Magical Creatures" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magical Creatures</a> *
<br><a data-href="Unique Abilities" href="\Unique Abilities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Unique Abilities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Constructed Itelligences" href="\Constructed Itelligences" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Constructed Itelligences</a> *
<br><a data-href="Magic Rituals" href="\Magic Rituals" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Magic Rituals</a> *


<br><a data-href="Paranormal Entities" href="\Paranormal Entities" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Paranormal Entities</a> *
<br><a data-href="Highstorms" href="\fantastical-elements\highstorms.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Stars" href="\Stars" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Stars</a> *
<br><a data-href="Planets" href="\Planets" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Planets</a> *
<br><a data-href="Moons" href="\Moons" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moons</a> *
<br><a data-href="Asteroids" href="\Asteroids" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Asteroids</a> *
<br><a data-href="Weathers and Storms" href="\Weathers and Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Weathers and Storms</a> *
<br><a data-href="Strange Worlds" href="\Strange Worlds" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Strange Worlds</a> *
<br><br>
<br><a data-href="Traps" href="\Traps" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Traps</a> *
<br><a data-href="Riddles and Puzzles" href="\Riddles and Puzzles" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Riddles and Puzzles</a> *
<br><a data-href="Forbidden Technologies" href="\Forbidden Technologies" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Forbidden Technologies</a> *
<br><a data-href="Crime" href="\Crime" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Crime</a> *
<br><a data-href="Illicit Goods and Services" href="\Illicit Goods and Services" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Illicit Goods and Services</a> *

<br><a data-href="Poison &amp; Venom" href="\Poison &amp; Venom" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Poison &amp; Venom</a> *


<br><a data-href="Disease" href="\Disease" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Disease</a> *
<br><a data-href="Cults" href="\Cults" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Cults</a> *
<br>* =  UNDER CONSTRUCTION]]></description><link>table-of-elements.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Table of Elements.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 18:24:07 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="_attachments\logo.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="_attachments\logo.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Appearance]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The Dwarves of Caitha are widely credited with creating the first unified currency in the world, laying the foundation for the economy for centuries to come.<br>
The Dwarven Crown, commonly referred to as just "Crown", the most enduring symbol of trade and wealth. These hexagonal coins, produced in the golden halls of <a data-href="Dhartahl" href="\Dhartahl" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dhartahl</a> have long been the predominant currency used throughout the diverse regions of Caitha.<br><br>Crowns minted in the forges of Dhartahl are hexagonal with a hexagonal hole in the middle. They are approximately 3.5 centimeters in diameter, and have a 5 mm thick border with fine stripes in the middle. Many coins are simple, but some of the golden coins have a symbol printed on them to commemorate an event or important person.<br>
<img alt="goldencrown.png" src="\lib\media\goldencrown.png"><br><br>The copper crown (CC), the silver crown (SC) and the golden crown (GC) are the primary denominations of this currency. 10 Copper Crowns make a silver crown, and 10 silver crowns make a golden crown.<br>
Copper Crowns, often referred to as "Coppers," serve as the basic unit of currency for everyday transactions. Silver Crowns, or "Silvers," are of higher value and commonly used for larger purchases, while Golden Crowns, known as "Goldens," are the most valuable you will encounter in your day to day. There are Platinum coins as well, though they are typically reserved for significant transactions and wealth storage.<br><br>The origins of the Crown can be traced back to the ancient forges of Dhartahl, where Dwarven metallurgists and craftsmen created these hexagonal coins during the <a data-href="Empire Wars" href="\Empire Wars" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Empire Wars</a> in an effort to create an economy that would be much stronger than that of their enemies - with success.<br>
The unification of these coins into a single currency system was a remarkable achievement in a world that had previously relied on a hodgepodge of barter systems and various forms of currency. The Dwarves' reputation for integrity and craftsmanship bolstered the acceptance of their coins among other civilizations.<br>
Centuries have passed since the Dwarven Crowns were first minted, yet they remain the backbone of Caitha's economic stability. The enduring trust in these coins is a testament to the unwavering commitment of the Dwarves to maintain the purity of their currency. Each Crown is carefully casted and pressed in Dhartahl, adhering to the traditional methods passed down through generations.]]></description><link>economics\currency\dwarven-crowns.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Economics/currency/Dwarven Crowns.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 22:45:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\goldencrown.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="lib\media\goldencrown.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Druidic Sacrifice]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The story of the Druidic Sacrifice is the story of perhaps the single most pivotal and solemn event in the annals of the known world, marking the end of the <a data-href="Era of Storms" href="\Era of Storms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Storms</a>. <br>In a time before the "<a data-href="Era of Legends" href="\timelines\era-of-legends.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Legends</a>" and the widespread adoption of the <a data-href="Druidic Calendar" href="\Druidic Calendar" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a> that we use today, Mages wielded the extraordinary ability to manipulate the world's weather through a potent form of magic. These wielders of natural forces sought to shape the world's climate, bringing about significant changes that, while awe-inspiring, led to unforeseen and dangerous consequences.<br>The unintended side effect of the Mages' extensive use of magic was the emergence of <a data-href="Highstorms" href="\Highstorms" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Highstorms</a>. These storms bore little resemblance to conventional storms, replacing lightning flashes with disconcerting moments of darkness and the deep, rolling thunder with high-pitched, eerie sounds.<br>
These storms disrupted the world's natural order and posed a severe threat to all of the known world. Many mages did not realise this, or were simply too hungry for power. Magic users split into two factions, the mighty mages continuing to wield the uncontrollable destructive forces, and the Druids, wanting to save the world from certain doom. They were quick to realize the gravity of their actions, as the number of Highstorms grew uncontrollably, endangering both the physical and metaphysical realms.<br>Brutal magical wars ensued, claiming more lives than we could count today on both sides, but in the end, the Druids emerged victorious.<br>Faced with the dangerous consequences to the degree of manipulation the natural world has seen, the Druid Circles recognized the need for a momentous and collective effort to rectify their past misdeeds. With unity and a deep commitment to protect their world, they embarked on a secretive and large-scale ritual to banish the Highstorms far beyond the borders of the known world.<br>However, this ritual came at an extraordinary cost. Every Druid involved in this endeavour succumbed to exhaustion, marking their sacrifice with their lives.<br>The Druids, who later established the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Time and the Calendar" data-href="Time and the Calendar" href="\timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a>, used this event as its official beginning.<br>Druids today regard the event as a crucial part of their heritage, and they have sworn to preserve Caitha as it is, ensuring the Highstorms remain at bay and refraining from further interference with the world's climate. Every new Druid is brought up with the knowledge that this great sacrifice may one day be required again.<br>In all parts of the world this degree of weather manipulation is outlawed today, and almost everywhere under penalty of death.<br>Nobody really knows what lies beyond the storms that encircle the world, and we may never find out.]]></description><link>historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Historical Elements/Legends and Tales/The Druidic Sacrifice.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 11:41:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Legends and Tales]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Below you can find a list of all currently published Legends and Tales from Caitha. Some consider them folklore, some consider them history. And who knows? Maybe a kernel of truth really lies in some of them.<br>
<br><a data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">The Druidic Sacrifice</a>
]]></description><link>historical-elements\legends-and-tales.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Historical Elements/Legends and Tales.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 11:42:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Maps]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>In this neat little collection you will (at some point) find all types of maps of Caitha I have created so far.<br>
For now, however, I can only show you this over on worldanvil:<br>
<a rel="noopener" class="external-link" title="eeeeeeee" href="https://www.worldanvil.com/w/caitha-sirnoodle/map/ca56c5e0-50ca-4cd4-9d00-7a8be2a1492c" target="_blank">https://www.worldanvil.com/w/caitha-sirnoodle/map/ca56c5e0-50ca-4cd4-9d00-7a8be2a1492c</a><br><br><br><br><br>]]></description><link>maps\maps.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Maps/Maps.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 15:50:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Time and the Calendar]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A single day on Caitha is roughly the same length as one on Earth. Time is being tracked throughout the day using a combination of sun-positioning, stable candles, water clocks, other mechanical or magical means and - depending on where you live - even using the weather.<br>
Mechanical clocks are technically available, though scarce, not very practical, and incredibly expensive.<br><br>The most widely adapted and established Calendar in Caitha is the <a data-href="Druidic Calendar" href="\Druidic Calendar" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Calendar</a> - a lunar calendar based on the moon phases of two out of the three <a data-href="Moons" href="\Moons" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Moons</a> of Caitha, Elydd, Nevi and Yova, developed by Druids in today's <a data-href="Ilora" href="\Ilora" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Ilora</a> based on their observance of the night sky and the seasons.<br>
This Calendar was later adopted and spread through the world through trade and politics by the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Palyra" data-href="Palyra" href="\Palyra" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Palyran Empire</a> during the <a data-href="Era of Legends" href="\timelines\era-of-legends.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Era of Legends</a>. The beginning of this calendar is marked by the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="The Druidic Sacrifice" data-href="The Druidic Sacrifice" href="\historical-elements\legends-and-tales\the-druidic-sacrifice.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Druidic Sacrifice</a>.<br><br>The week is made up of 8 days and based on the blue moon Nevi, which takes 16 days for a full cycle. Every week starts on either a full moon or a new moon on Moonday and goes over firsday, seconday, thirday, fourday, fiveday, sixday, and sevenday.<br><br>A Month on Caitha is made up of 37 days and is based on the white moon Elydd, which takes a full 74 days for a full cycle.  Each new moon for Elydd roughly marks the beginning of a new season.<br>First Bloom<br>
First month of the year, and the arrival of spring. This month celebrates the blossoming of the flora.<br>Goldengrass<br>
Second month of the year, as the sun becomes more intense, this month is marked by an increase in sunlight and warmth leading into summer.<br>Emberfall<br>
Third month of the year, marked by occasional wildfires and dry season in <a data-href="Palyra" href="\Palyra" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Palyra</a>.<br>First Harvest<br>
Fourth month of the year, named after the first harvest that occurs.<br>Seawind<br>
Fifth month of the year, as the winds off the sea become more noticeable, this month signifies the end of summer, and beginning of autumn.<br>Second Harvest<br>
Sixth month of the year, marked by the gathering of resources and another harvest before winter sets in.<br>Sunfade<br>
Seventh month of the year, as the sun fades and rainy season sets in, this month is marked by abundant coastal precipitation.<br>Mistrend<br>
Eighth month of the year, characterised by the season's capacity to shroud and renew the land.<br><br>A full year on Caitha takes 296 days, or 8 months. Every season is roughly two months long.]]></description><link>timelines\time-and-the-calendar.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Timelines/Time and the Calendar.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 15:57:50 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>